
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><?da-xref-anchor-style superscripted?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1229</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">iovs</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IOVS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Investigative Ophthalmology &amp; Visual Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0146-0404</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1552-5783</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Association for Research in Vision and Ophthalmology</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12889168</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12889168.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12889168</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12889168</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41642026</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1167/iovs.67.2.18</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IOVS-25-44353</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Glaucoma</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category"><subject>Glaucoma</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Molecular Mechanisms and Therapeutic Potentials of Engrailed-1 in Fibrotic Scar Formation Post Glaucoma Filtration Surgery</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="runhead">EN1 in Scarring After GFS and Target Therapy</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names initials="W">Wangdu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaomin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names initials="J">Julong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiangji</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names initials="L">Lin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Ophthalmology, The Third Affiliated Hospital of Chongqing Medical University, Chongqing, China</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
<label>#</label>Correspondence: Lin Xie, Department of Ophthalmology, The Third Affiliated Hospital of Chongqing Medical University, 1 Shuanghu Rd., Chongqing 401120, China; <email>xielin@hospital.cqmu.edu.cn</email>.</corresp><fn id="afn1"><label>*</label><p>YL and WL contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>2</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>67</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">506984</issue-id><elocation-id>18</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2026</year></date><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>05</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>11</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-02-11 10:25:13.880"><day>11</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright 2026 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2026</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="iovs-67-2-18.pdf"><?pdf-name iovs-67-2-18.pdf?><?pdf-size 41830783?><?pdf-md5 e01459a814f3df939d35970f318b7530?><?pdf-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?pdf-cloudpmc-urn urn:app:dfb8/12889168/e01459a814f3/iovs-67-2-18.pdf?></self-uri><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="iovs-67-2-18.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Purpose</title><p>Conjunctival scarring is a major cause of glaucoma filtration surgery (GFS) failure, necessitating effective antifibrotic strategies. This study investigated the role of engrailed-1 (EN1) in conjunctival fibrosis and evaluated the therapeutic potential of EN1-targeted biomaterials for antiscarring in post-GFS patients.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Fibrotic models were developed using TGF-β2–induced human Tenon fibroblasts (HTFs) and a rat GFS model. EN1 was identified as a key therapeutic target using RNA interference, transcriptome sequencing, chromatin immunoprecipitation–qPCR, and dual-luciferase assays. Exosomes (Exos) loaded with EN1 small interfering RNA were encapsulated in a GelMA hydrogel to form the Gel-Exo-siEN1 composite material.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>EN1 expression was significantly elevated in TGF-β2–stimulated HTFs and conjunctival scar tissue post GFS. Inhibition of EN1 reduced TGF-β2–induced proliferation and migration in HTFs and decreased fibrosis-related gene expression. These effects may be mediated through the Yes-related protein/transcriptional co-activator PDZ-binding motif and SMAD3 pathways. Assays confirmed that EN1 inhibition suppressed proliferation and migration and downregulated fibrosis markers like fibronectin, collagen I, and α-smooth muscle actin. Western blot analysis showed increased Yes-related protein/transcriptional co-activator PDZ-binding motif expression after TGF-β2 induction, which was reduced by verteporfin. Chromatin immunoprecipitation–PCR confirmed that SMAD3 binds to the EN1 promoter, regulating its expression. Exo analysis showed Exo-siEN1 maintained stability and effectively delivered siEN1, leading to significant EN1 knockdown and reduced fibrosis in rat Tenon's fibroblasts. Gel-Exo-siEN1 treatment significantly increased functional bleb area, reduced IOP, and decreased collagen deposition and inflammatory cell infiltration in the conjunctiva after GFS.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Gel-Exo-siEN1 is a promising strategy for preventing postsurgical scarring and improving the outcomes of glaucoma surgery.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>glaucoma filtration surgery</kwd><kwd>antiscarring therapy</kwd><kwd>engrailed-1</kwd><kwd>exosome</kwd><kwd>GelMA</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="15"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Glaucoma, a major cause of irreversible blindness, results from elevated IOP, damaging the optic nerve and causing visual field defects.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Filtering surgery is the primary treatment, but excessive scarring often leads to surgical failure.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> Although drugs like mitomycin C (MMC) and 5-fluorouracil improve success rates, their use is limited by adverse effects.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> A deeper understanding of cytokine regulation in scar formation is needed, highlighting the importance of research into precise mechanisms and long-term strategies for preventing scarring.</p><p>Engrailed-1 (EN1), a vital homeobox protein transcription factor, plays a critical role in tissue and organ development. Recent studies have found the increased EN1 expression in various fibroblast subsets, where it amplifies signals for myofibroblast differentiation via the TGF-β pathway.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> Skin injury causes EN1-negative fibroblasts to express EN1 owing to increased tension, leading to the production of 40% to 50% of scar-forming fibroblasts and resulting in scar formation.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> These findings highlight the importance of EN1 in tissue damage and repair, suggesting potential targets for antiscar treatments. However, its involvement in conjunctival fibrosis after glaucoma filtration surgery (GFS) remains uncertain. Therefore, a thorough investigation into the role and mechanisms of EN1 in scar formation after GFS is essential for developing preventive strategies.</p><p>Therefore, in this study, we examined the role of EN1 in the formation of conjunctival fibrosis and its regulatory mechanisms. Subsequently, we developed an EN1-targeted composite biomaterial, investigating its effectiveness in inhibiting the development of conjunctival fibrosis after GFS.</p><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Human Tenon's Fibroblasts (HTFs) Isolation and Identification</title><p>Small Tenon's tissue biopsies were obtained intraoperatively from six patients undergoing strabismus surgery. All participants had no history of prior ocular surgery and were free of systemic or ocular diseases other than strabismus. Tenon's capsule tissues collected intraoperatively were cut into small pieces (0.5 mm<sup>3</sup>). These samples were cultured in DMEM with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) and 1% penicillin/streptomycin at 37°C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. HTFs were identified using rabbit antivimentin and mouse anticytokeratin antibodies by immunofluorescence, with experiments conducted on cell passages 3 to 6 (passages 3–6) HTFs.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Immunofluorescence</title><p>Tissue sections and HTFs on coverslips were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde for 15 minutes, treated with 0.2% Triton solution for 10 minutes, and blocked with 1% BSA for 30 minutes. They were then incubated with primary antibodies overnight at 4°C, followed by incubation with secondary antibodies in the dark at room temperature for 2 hours, and observed under a confocal fluorescence microscope.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Transfection HTFs With EN1 Small Interfering RNA (siRNA)</title><p>We diluted 10 µL of NC siRNA or EN1 siRNA in 250 µL Opti-MEM and diluted 5.0 µL Lipofectamine 3000 transfection reagent in 250 µL Opti-MEM. We mixed the siRNA solution with the transfection reagent. We added the transfection complex into a six-well cell plates (500 µL per well). We extracted total RNA from cells in each experimental group for qPCR experiments, extracted total protein from cells in each experimental group, and analyzed the expression levels of proteins using Western blot.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Quantitative RT-PCR and Western Blotting</title><p>RT-PCR was performed by using SYBR green Master Mix (Vazyme, Nanjng, China). The relative quantification of EN1 levels was calculated using the 2<sup>−△△ Ct</sup> method. The primer sequences used were available in <xref rid="iovs-67-2-18_s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>.</p><p>Proteins were electrophoresed on 12.5% SDS-PAGE gels, transferred electrophoretically to polyvinylidene fluoride membranes (Millipore, Boston, MA, USA), and blocked with 5% skimmed milk for 60 minutes. Afterward, the proteins were incubated with the corresponding primary antibodies at 4°C for 12 hours. The antibodies used are available in <xref rid="iovs-67-2-18_s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S2</xref>. On day 2, membranes were incubated with the secondly antibodies for 60 minutes. Finally, the protein bands were visualized with enhanced chemiluminescence solution (Millipore).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title>Cell Counting Kit-8 (CCK-8), Cell Scratch, and Transwell Assays</title><p>Transfection HTFs with EN1 siRNA, cells were categorized into four groups: control, TGF-β2, siEN1 + TGF-β2, and siNC + TGF-β2. The TGF-β2 concentration was maintained at 10 ng/mL, and the final siRNA concentration was 100 nM. After overnight incubation, serum-free high-glucose DMEM was used. Subsequently, a 24-hour starvation treatment ensued. After the respective interventions, the proliferation potential of HTFs cells was assessed with a CCK-8 assay. The migration of HTFs were assessed by cell scratch and transwell assays.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title>Chromatin Immunoprecipitation (ChIP)–Quantitative PCR (qPCR)</title><p>In brief, cells were cross-linked using formaldehyde at a final concentration of 1%. After cessation of cross-linking with glycine, chromatin was sheared to 100 to 300 bp using sonication. The anti–SMAD3-Tag antibody (Abcam, ab208182; Cambridge, UK) and protein G beads were used to pull down the target protein, which was then digested with proteinase K, followed by amplification via qPCR. The primers for the EN1 promoter were available in <xref rid="iovs-67-2-18_s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S3</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-7"><title>Transcriptome Sequencing</title><p>Total RNA was extracted and riboxomal RNA removed using the GenSeq riboxomal RNA Removal Kit (GenSeq, Dublin, Ireland). Sequencing libraries were constructed and sequenced on Illumina NovaSeq 6000 with 150-bp paired-end reads. Clean reads were obtained and alignment to the reference genome with hisat2 software. Raw count data were obtained and analyzed using edgeR software. Genes with a fold change of 2 or more and a false discovery rate of 0.5 or less were considered significantly differentially expressed. Clustering, Gene Ontology enrichment, and Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) pathway analyses were conducted on differentially expression genes.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-8"><title>Dual-Luciferase Reporter Assay</title><p>Predicted EN1 binding sites on the fibronectin (FN) promoter were identified via the JASPAR database. The FN promoter sequence was synthesized and inserted into the pGL3-basic vector by Wuhan Jinkairui Biotechnology Co (Wuhan, China). For transfection, plasmid DNA of the FN promoter and EN1 transcription factor were dissolved at a 10:1 ratio. Then, 2 µL of Lipofectamine 2000 was added to the serum-free DMEM. The original culture medium was replaced with the transfection complex (500 µL) in the wells. Subsequently, the medium was changed to complete DMEM supplemented with 10% FBS. Relative activities of firefly luciferase and Renilla luciferase were assessed using the Dual-Luciferase Reporter Gene Assay Kit.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-9"><title>Extraction and Identification of Exosomes (Exos)</title><p>Exos were extracted from HEK-293 cells by differential centrifugation. After removing the supernatant, the pellet was resuspended in PBS to obtain the Exos. The Exos were identified as follows. <list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>•</label><p>Transmission electron microscopy: Exos were deposited onto a copper grid and stained with 3% phosphotungstic acid solution and observed by transmission electron microscopy.</p></list-item><list-item><label>•</label><p>Measurement of Exos size: diluted Exos samples were drawn into a syringe and analyzed using nanoparticle tracking analysis to determine the vesicle diameter.</p></list-item><list-item><label>•</label><p>Identification of Exos markers: Western blot analysis was performed to detect the expression of the markers, including TSG101, CD81, and CD63.</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="sec2-10"><title>Electroporation of Exos With siEN1 and Degradation of siEN1</title><p>The sequences of the EN1 siRNAs used are available <xref rid="iovs-67-2-18_s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S4</xref>. According to previous studies,<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> 10 µL of Exos samples at a concentration of 10<sup>12</sup> particles/mL was mixed with 100 µg of siEN1, dissolved in 400 µL of electroporation buffer (25 mM KCl, 1.15 mM potassium phosphate, and 21% Opti-MEM, pH 7.2). Electroporation was performed with 20 pulses at 0.7 kV, each lasting 0.35 seconds, and chromatography was used to remove free siRNA. Equal amounts of free siRNA and Exo-loaded EN1 siRNA were incubated in PBS with 50% FBS. At different time points, siRNA was extracted using a small RNA extraction kit. siRNA degradation was assessed via agarose gel electrophoresis.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-11"><title>Intracellular Uptake</title><p>According to previous literature,<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> on postoperative day 10, Tenon's capsule fibroblasts were isolated from the tissue surrounding the filtration bleb of rats. Wes mixed 4 µL of PKH26 with 1 mL of Diluent C solvent and added to the Exo suspension loaded or unloaded with FITC-labeled EN1 siRNA. The mixture was centrifuged at 100,000×<italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 70 minutes at 4°C, the pellet resuspended in PBS. The fluorescently labeled Exo-siEN1 was co-incubated with rat Tenon's capsule fibroblasts for 6 hours. After co-incubation, 4% paraformaldehyde was added to fix the cells for 30 minutes. The cells were then incubated with DAPI at room temperature for 10 minutes, washed with PBS, and observed under a laser confocal microscope.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-12"><title>Preparation and Characterization of Gel-Exo-siEN1 Hydrogel</title><p>According to previous studies,<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> pre-prepared GelMA hydrogel was mixed with Exo-siEN1 (final concentration of 200 µg/mL) to form Gel-Exo-siEN1 hydrogel. DiR-labeled Exos were used to prepare Gel-DiR-Exo-siEN1 hydrogel, and fluorescence confocal microscopy was used to observe Exo distribution. The Gel-Exo-siEN1 hydrogel was freeze-dried overnight in a lyophilizer, the morphology was observed under scanning electron microscopy. Moreover, the Gel-Exo-siEN1 hydrogel was placed in PBS, collected daily, and replaced with an equal volume of PBS; the cumulative release of Exos was measured using a BCA protein assay kit. Biocompatibility was assessed by live/dead staining.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-13"><title>Establishment of Rat GFS Models</title><p>Male Sprague-Dawley rats weighing 200 to 300<italic toggle="yes">g</italic> were selected. Following the procedure outlined in previous literature,<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> rats were anesthetized with 3% sodium pentobarbital (0.1 mL/100<italic toggle="yes">g</italic>), 0.5% oxybuprocaine hydrochloride eye drops were applied, and preoperative IOP was measured. A conjunctival flap (1.5–3.0 mm) was created at the temporal upper limbus. Using a 25G needle, an anterior chamber puncture was made 0.3 mm from the corneal edge to release aqueous humor. A 3- to 4-mm microtube was prepared, and the drainage tube was carefully inserted into the needle hub. It was implanted into the anterior chamber, approximately 3 mm from the limbus along the puncture tract, with the other end tucked under the conjunctival flap. Closure was done with 10-0 nylon sutures. Postoperatively, chloramphenicol eye drops were given. The rats were randomly assigned into four groups: (1) control group, in which no additional treatment was administered to the bulbar conjunctiva after surgery; (2) the MMC group, in which a solution of 0.4 mg/mL of MMC was applied to a small piece of cotton pad and placed under the conjunctival flap for 2 minutes, followed by rinsing with saline; and (3) the Gel-Exo group (Exos loaded with scrambled siRNA) and the (4) Gel-Exo-siEN1 group (Exos loaded with siEN1) received the same composite hydrogel formulation. The corresponding gel (Gel-Exo or Gel-Exo-siEN1) was applied over the conjunctival suture in each group, respectively.</p><p>Postoperative ocular inflammation, IOP, and the presence and viability of filtering vesicles were recorded. In the Kaplan–Meier survival analysis of filtration vesicles, filtration vesicle failure was operationally defined as the presence of flat, vascularized, or scarred filtration vesicles alongside normal anterior chamber depth. The temporal end point for follicle failure was established as the date of the initial of two consecutive examinations in which the observer determined follicle failure. IOP measurements were conducted using the Tono-Pen hand-held pressure leveling tonometer, with preoperative IOP values serving as the baseline. The ultimate recorded IOP value was determined as the mean of three measurements, with all assessments conducted by a consistent experimenter at the same time each day. All postoperative outcome assessments were conducted by independent observers who were fully masked to group allocation throughout the evaluation process.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-14"><title>Hematoxylin and Eosin Staining</title><p>After fixation and paraffin embedding, the sections were deparaffinized using xylene, followed by gradual ethanol hydration and rinsing with water. The sections were treated with hematoxylin solution for 5 minutes, followed by eosin staining for 5 minutes. After clarification in xylene, the sections were mounted.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-15"><title>Masson Staining</title><p>For Masson's staining, sections were stained with Weigert's hematoxylin solution for 5 minutes, then differentiated in 1% hydrochloric acid alcohol. They were subsequently stained with Light Green and Acid Fuchsin for 5 to 10 minutes and treated with phosphomolybdic acid solution for 3 to 5 minutes. Aniline Blue was used for counterstaining for 5 minutes, followed by 2% acetic acid differentiation for 1 minute. Sections were clarified with xylene and mounted before observation and image acquisition under a microscope.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-16"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>All quantitative data are presented as mean ± SD and analyzed by GraphPad Prism 8. Student <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> tests were used for statistical analysis between two groups, and one-way ANOVA was conducted among multiple groups, followed by Tukey's test for post hoc analysis. A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value of less than 0.05 was considered to be statistically significant. Additionally, all experiments were performed in triplicate at least.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec3"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3-1"><title>EN1 Expression Was Upregulated in TGF-β2–Induction HTFs and Conjunctival Scar Tissue</title><p>Primary HTFs were isolated and confirmed by specific vimentin expression (<xref rid="iovs-67-2-18_s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S1</xref>). HTFs were stimulated with varying concentrations of TGF-β2 (2, 5, 10, and 20 ng/mL) for 24 hours. Western blot analysis indicated significant increases in -smooth muscle actin (α-SMA), collagen I, and FN expression compared with controls. Moreover, EN1 expression notably increased after TGF-β2 induction (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), particularly at 10 ng/mL and 20 ng/mL (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>A). Additionally, EN1 expression increased significantly after 24 hours (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>B). Notably, EN1, which was minimally expressed or absent in normal HTFs, showed elevated nuclear expression after TGF-β2 induction (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>C), indicating that TGF-β2 could upregulate EN1 expression in HTFs. A rat model of GFS was established via microtube implantation (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>A). EN1 expression was significantly elevated in conjunctival scar tissue of GFS rats compared with that of controls (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figs. 2</xref>B–D).</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) EN1, α-SMA, collagen I and FN protein expression after different TGF-β2 concentrations intervened in HTFs. (<bold>B</bold>) TGF-β2 (10 ng/mL) intervened in HTFs at different times of EN1 protein expression. (<bold>C</bold>) Effect of TGF-β2 (10 ng/mL) on EN1 expression in HTFs; <italic toggle="yes">scale</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">bar</italic>, 50 µm. <italic toggle="yes">Scale bar</italic>, 50 µm. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> ≧ 3; *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05; **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01; ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="iovs-67-2-18-f001.jpg"><?image-name iovs-67-2-18-f001.jpg?><?image-size 97314?><?image-md5 99552b8332179a107e239ba65b391251?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 2126?><?image-original-width 2050?><?image-scaled-height 708?><?image-scaled-width 683?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/dfb8/12889168/99552b833217/iovs-67-2-18-f001.jpg?><?thumb-name iovs-67-2-18-f001.gif?><?thumb-size 7242?><?thumb-md5 a7be2594d6ce4de7a6cafcdf9e4f793e?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 104?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/dfb8/12889168/a7be2594d6ce/iovs-67-2-18-f001.gif?></graphic></fig><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Successful construction of rat GFS model. (<bold>B</bold>, <bold>C</bold>) Expression of EN1 gene and protein in conjunctival scar tissue after GFS surgery. (<bold>D</bold>) Immunofluorescence observation of EN1 protein expression in conjunctival scar tissue after GFS surgery; <italic toggle="yes">scale</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">bar</italic>, 100 µm. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> ≧ 3. **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="iovs-67-2-18-f002.jpg"><?image-name iovs-67-2-18-f002.jpg?><?image-size 74069?><?image-md5 d1e42e43d101a5c280a43549d59172d7?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 1171?><?image-original-width 2050?><?image-scaled-height 390?><?image-scaled-width 683?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/dfb8/12889168/d1e42e43d101/iovs-67-2-18-f002.jpg?><?thumb-name iovs-67-2-18-f002.gif?><?thumb-size 7737?><?thumb-md5 6909af38fd0a4970fdb978e0c72fe2b5?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 80?><?thumb-scaled-width 140?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/dfb8/12889168/6909af38fd0a/iovs-67-2-18-f002.gif?></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-2"><title>SiEN1 Suppressed TGF-β2–Induced HTFs Proliferation, Migration, Myofibroblast Transformation, and ECM Synthesis</title><p>To explore the role of EN1 in TGF-β2–induced proliferation and migration of HTFs, we used EN1 siRNA to suppress EN1 gene expression; EN1 expression levels were significantly decreased as evidenced by qPCR results (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>A). Subsequently, the most efficient EN1 siRNA sequence was chosen for cell transfection, leading to a significant decreased expression of EN1 at the protein level (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>B). Scratch assays demonstrated that siEN1 alleviated HTFs migration induced by TGF-β2 (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>C), and CCK-8 assays revealed that siEN1 inhibited TGF-β2–induced HTFs proliferation (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>D). Furthermore, transwell assays affirmed the alleviation of TGF-β2–induced migration ability by siEN1 (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>E). The transition of HTFs into myofibroblasts and ECM synthesis was also evaluated by assessing α-SMA, collagen I, and FN expression. Western blot and qPCR results demonstrated that EN1 siRNAs downregulated the expression of α-SMA, FN, and collagen I proteins induced by TGF-β2 (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figs. 4</xref>A–D). Immunofluorescence further confirmed that inhibiting EN1 expression exerted a certain inhibitory effect on the myofibroblast transformation process (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figs. 4</xref>E–H).</p><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Validation of EN1 gene expression after siRNA knockdown by qPCR. (<bold>B</bold>) Western blot detection of EN1 expression in HTFs after transfection with EN1 siRNA. (<bold>C</bold>) Scratch assay to observe the effect of siEN1 on TGF-β2–induced HTFs proliferation and migration. <italic toggle="yes">Scale bar</italic>, 0.2 mm. (<bold>D</bold>) CCK-8 analysis of the effect of siEN1 on TGF-β2–induced proliferation of HTFs. (<bold>E</bold>) Transwell assay to evaluate the effect of siEN1 on the migration ability of TGF-β2–induced HTFs. <italic toggle="yes">Scale bar</italic>, 100 µm. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> ≧ 3. ns, not significant. **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="iovs-67-2-18-f003.jpg"><?image-name iovs-67-2-18-f003.jpg?><?image-size 130238?><?image-md5 22935495fb9292631464afa047770db0?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 1255?><?image-original-width 2024?><?image-scaled-height 418?><?image-scaled-width 674?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/dfb8/12889168/22935495fb92/iovs-67-2-18-f003.jpg?><?thumb-name iovs-67-2-18-f003.gif?><?thumb-size 8938?><?thumb-md5 4bc291c6935bb9fee4a2de280557d12a?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 80?><?thumb-scaled-width 129?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/dfb8/12889168/4bc291c6935b/iovs-67-2-18-f003.gif?></graphic></fig><fig position="float" id="fig4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Western blot to detect the expression of fibrosis-related proteins in HTFs after EN1 siRNA transfection. (<bold>B</bold>–<bold>D</bold>) qPCR to detect the expression of FN, collagen I, and α-SMA gene in HTFs after EN1 siRNA transfection. (<bold>E</bold>–<bold>H</bold>) Immunofluorescence to observe the effect of siEN1 on the expression of α-SMA, collagen I, F-actin, and FN proteins in HTFs. <italic toggle="yes">S</italic><italic toggle="yes">cale</italic> bar, 20 µm. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> ≧ 3. ns, not significant. **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="iovs-67-2-18-f004.jpg"><?image-name iovs-67-2-18-f004.jpg?><?image-size 157298?><?image-md5 f4420c46ec0a8f503a9a0d56a356a2e6?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 2302?><?image-original-width 2050?><?image-scaled-height 767?><?image-scaled-width 683?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/dfb8/12889168/f4420c46ec0a/iovs-67-2-18-f004.jpg?><?thumb-name iovs-67-2-18-f004.gif?><?thumb-size 8541?><?thumb-md5 ca3892d44fc99aa13e859e6da51ce1f7?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 112?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/dfb8/12889168/ca3892d44fc9/iovs-67-2-18-f004.gif?></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-3"><title>Gene Expression Profiles of HTFs After siEN1 Intervention</title><p>To explore the downstream mechanism of EN1, HTFs were transfected with siEN1 and siNC, followed by TGF-β2 stimulation and transcriptome sequencing. Compared with the siNC + TGF-β2 group, 1868 mRNAs were significantly differentially expressed (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>A). Clustering analysis confirmed distinct gene expression patterns between the groups, validating the experiment's reproducibility (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>B). KEGG pathway analysis indicated significant enrichment in pathways such as ECM–receptor interaction (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>C). Gene Ontology analysis of the downregulated mRNAs in the siEN1 + TGF-β2 group revealed enrichment in processes like extracellular matrix (ECM) organization and components such as the collagen-containing ECM (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>D). Using the JASPAR database, we predicted the binding sites between the transcription factor EN1 and potential target genes FN, collagen I, and α-SMA in their promoter sites. We selected FN, collagen I, and α-SMA for a dual-luciferase reporter assay, which showed significantly increased fluorescence enzyme activity in cells transfected with the EN1 overexpression plasmid, but no significant change in the vector group. This finding indicated that EN1 can bind to promoters of FN, collagen I, and α-SMA, enhancing luciferase gene expression and confirming a targeted regulatory relationship between them (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>EF). These findings suggested that the significant gene expression changes in HTFs after siEN1 transfection are mainly related to ECM organization and remodeling, highlighting EN1's crucial role in fibrosis.</p><fig position="float" id="fig5" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Volcano plot showing differentially expressed genes between the two groups (<italic toggle="yes">red dots</italic> indicate an increase in gene expression level, <italic toggle="yes">blue dots</italic> indicate a decrease in gene expression, and <italic toggle="yes">gray dots</italic> indicate no significant difference in gene expression). (<bold>B</bold>) Heatmap revealing the similarity and difference in the gene expression patterns of HTFs between the two groups. (<bold>C</bold>) KEGG enrichment analysis of relevant differential genes between the two groups. (<bold>D</bold>) Gene Ontology enrichment analysis of relevant differential genes between the two groups. (<bold>E</bold>, <bold>F</bold>) Dual luciferase activity assay revealed that EN1 significantly increases the transcriptional activity of fibrosis-related genes. ns, not significant. **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="iovs-67-2-18-f005.jpg"><?image-name iovs-67-2-18-f005.jpg?><?image-size 185464?><?image-md5 6f730ee3c282f6d13bb0c70d568986ce?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 2500?><?image-original-width 1955?><?image-scaled-height 1000?><?image-scaled-width 782?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/dfb8/12889168/6f730ee3c282/iovs-67-2-18-f005.jpg?><?thumb-name iovs-67-2-18-f005.gif?><?thumb-size 8360?><?thumb-md5 15d28cd54a6d923f54b9203ad87db542?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 128?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/dfb8/12889168/15d28cd54a6d/iovs-67-2-18-f005.gif?></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-4"><title>The Yes-Related Protein/Transcriptional Coactivator PDZ-Binding Motif (YAP/TAZ) Pathway May Modulate the Upregulation of EN1 Expression in TGF-β2–Induced HTFs in a SMAD3-Dependent Manner</title><p>The YAP pathway may regulate EN1 expression. We observed increased YAP/TAZ protein levels following TGF-β2 induction, particularly with 10 ng/mL TGF-β2, which matched EN1 expression patterns (<xref rid="iovs-67-2-18_s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S2</xref>). Verteporfin, a YAP inhibitor, significantly reduced YAP, TAZ, and EN1 protein expression levels. To further investigate the YAP–EN1 relationship, we examined YAP's effect on the TGF-β/SMAD signaling pathway. In the verteporfin + TGF-β2 group, SMAD3 and p-SMAD3 levels were decreased (<xref rid="iovs-67-2-18_s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S3</xref>A). Immunofluorescence confirmed that YAP inhibition suppressed TGF-β2–induced nuclear expression of SMAD3 and EN1 (<xref rid="iovs-67-2-18_s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S3</xref>B). Using JASPAR, we predicted SMAD3 binding sites on the EN1 promoter (<xref rid="iovs-67-2-18_s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S3</xref>C) and designed SMAD3 primers for ChIP-PCR. The results showed that SMAD3 binds to the EN1 promoter region after TGF-β2 stimulation, affecting its transcription (<xref rid="iovs-67-2-18_s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. S3</xref>D).</p></sec><sec id="sec3-5"><title>Encapsulation of EN1 siRNA</title><p>A diagram of the isolation of Exos is shown in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>A. Primary rat Tenon's capsule fibroblasts were cultured, exhibiting spindle-shaped morphology and positive vimentin staining (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>B). The siRNA sequences targeting the EN1 were selected (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>C). Particle size analysis indicated an average size of approximately 130 nm for both Exo and Exo-siEN1 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>D), transmission electron microscopy showed typical vesicular morphology for Exo-siEN1 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>E), and Western blot confirmed Exo markers CD63, CD81, and TSG101 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>F), verifying successful Exo isolation and consistent integrity after siRNA encapsulation. Confocal microscopy confirmed colocalization of siEN1 and Exos, suggesting successful encapsulation via electroporation (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>E). Agarose gel electrophoresis showed naked siEN1 degradation after 4 hours in plasma, while Exo-encapsulated EN1-siRNA remained stable for 16 hours, indicating Exo encapsulation could effectively protect EN1-siRNA from degradation by nucleases (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>G).</p><fig position="float" id="fig6" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Pattern diagram of the material construction. (<bold>B</bold>) Identification of rat Tenon's capsule fibroblasts. (<bold>C</bold>) Verification of EN1 siRNA expression after transfection by qPCR. (<bold>D</bold>) Particle size detection of Exos. (<bold>E</bold>) Transmission electron micrograph of Exos (<italic toggle="yes">scale</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">bar</italic>, 200 nm) and co-localization of FITC-labeled siEN1 within Exos. (<bold>F</bold>) Western blot detection of exosomal marker proteins. (<bold>G</bold>) Agarose gel electrophoresis to detect serum stability of Exo-siEN1. (<bold>H</bold>) Physical diagram of Gel–Exo-siEN1 composite hydrogel preparation. (<bold>I</bold>) Confocal microscopy to observe the distribution of fluorescently labeled Exo in the hydrogel. (<bold>J</bold>) Scanning electron microscopy to detect the structural features of the material, <italic toggle="yes">scale</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">bar</italic>, 1 µm. (<bold>K</bold>) Experimental release of Exos from the hydrogel in an in vitro environment. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> ≧ 3. ns, not significant. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="iovs-67-2-18-f006.jpg"><?image-name iovs-67-2-18-f006.jpg?><?image-size 155345?><?image-md5 82f523ffab7d9934bc91323388f78bf7?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 2497?><?image-original-width 2050?><?image-scaled-height 832?><?image-scaled-width 683?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/dfb8/12889168/82f523ffab7d/iovs-67-2-18-f006.jpg?><?thumb-name iovs-67-2-18-f006.gif?><?thumb-size 8988?><?thumb-md5 560f26cdd72be3cc84818f80e951884c?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 122?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/dfb8/12889168/560f26cdd72b/iovs-67-2-18-f006.gif?></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-6"><title>Construction, Characterization of Gel-Exo-siEN1, and Intracellular Uptake of Exo-siEN1 by Rat Tenon's Capsule Fibroblasts</title><p>Schematic and actual images of the preparation of Gel-Exo-siEN1 are presented in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>H. Exo-siEN1 was evenly distributed in the gel without obvious aggregation, and the fluorescence signal was approximately consistent in different areas (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>I). Scanning electron microscopy showed that Exos were successfully loaded onto the GelMA hydrogel (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>J). Furthermore, the release curve of Gel-Exo-siEN1 showed that Exo-siEN1 could achieve a cumulative release rate of 78.45 ± 3.16% within 14 days, demonstrating its potential for slow release of Exos (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>K). Confocal microscopy showed PKH26-labled Exo-siEN1 appeared abundantly in the cytoplasm, confirming that Exos released from GelMA hydrogel could be effectively uptake by fibroblasts (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>A). Western blot and qPCR were used to evaluate the inhibitory effect of Gel-Exo-siEN1 on EN1 expression. Compared with the control group, Gel-Exo-siEN1 successfully suppressed EN1 mRNA and protein expression (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>B).</p><fig position="float" id="fig7" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Confocal microscope observation of cellular phagocytosis of Exos, <italic toggle="yes">scale</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">bar</italic>, 50 µm. (<bold>B</bold>) Western blot to detect the effect of Gel-Exo-siEN1 on EN1 expression. (<bold>C</bold>) Live/dead experiments were performed to evaluate the biocompatibility of the materials. S<italic toggle="yes">cale</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">bar</italic>, 100 µm. (<bold>D</bold>) CCK-8 to observe the effect of the materials on cell proliferation. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> ≧ 3. ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="iovs-67-2-18-f007.jpg"><?image-name iovs-67-2-18-f007.jpg?><?image-size 313087?><?image-md5 c77e108f7b2a25409d557c0ea3da6166?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 2500?><?image-original-width 1970?><?image-scaled-height 1000?><?image-scaled-width 788?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/dfb8/12889168/c77e108f7b2a/iovs-67-2-18-f007.jpg?><?thumb-name iovs-67-2-18-f007.gif?><?thumb-size 9751?><?thumb-md5 f4353819c8e19455dc790bcd6f16cc83?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 127?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/dfb8/12889168/f4353819c8e1/iovs-67-2-18-f007.gif?></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-7"><title>In Vitro Cytotoxicity Assessment and Antifibrotic Effects of Gel-Exo-siEN1</title><p>The biocompatibility of the materials was evaluated using the CCK-8 assay and live/dead staining. As shown in <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figures 7</xref>C, <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>D, Gel-Exo-siEN1 exhibited good biocompatibility and was suitable for subsequent in vivo experiments. The CCK-8 assay results showed that Gel-Exo-siEN1 could inhibit the proliferation of rat Tenon's capsule fibroblasts induced by TGF-β2 (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>A). Scratch assays and transwell assays results showed that the TGF-β2–induced migration effect was attenuated by Gel-Exo-siEN (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figs. 8</xref>B, <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>C). Compared with the TGF-β2–treated group, Gel-Exo-siEN1 significantly reduced the protein expression of α-SMA, FN, and collagen I induced by TGF-β2 (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>D).</p><fig position="float" id="fig8" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) CCK-8 analysis of the effect of Gel-Exo-siEN1 on TGF-β2–induced proliferation of rat Tenon's capsule fibroblasts. (<bold>B</bold>) Scratch assay to observe the effect of Gel-Exo-siEN1 on the TGF-β2–induced migration of rat Tenon's capsule fibroblasts. <italic toggle="yes">Scale bar</italic>, 0.2 mm. (<bold>C</bold>) Transwell assay to assess the effect of Gel-Exo-siEN1 on TGF-β2–induced migratory ability of rat Tenon's capsule fibroblasts. <italic toggle="yes">Scale bar</italic>, 100 µm. (<bold>D</bold>) The effect of Gel-Exo-siEN1 on the expression of α-SMA, FN, and collagen I proteins in TGF-β2–induced cells. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> ≧ 3. ns, not significant. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="iovs-67-2-18-f008.jpg"><?image-name iovs-67-2-18-f008.jpg?><?image-size 141237?><?image-md5 dfc2049677da5c29c9100582cb43ee72?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 1964?><?image-original-width 2050?><?image-scaled-height 654?><?image-scaled-width 683?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/dfb8/12889168/dfc2049677da/iovs-67-2-18-f008.jpg?><?thumb-name iovs-67-2-18-f008.gif?><?thumb-size 8204?><?thumb-md5 2d697a324ab5897be0e2b0f1ee10055b?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 96?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/dfb8/12889168/2d697a324ab5/iovs-67-2-18-f008.gif?></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-8"><title>The Role of Gel-Exo-siEN1 Hydrogel in Antifibrotic Effects After Rat GFS Surgery</title><p>Based on these results, we established a rat GFS model and observed the morphological changes of filtration blebs using a slit lamp (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>A). The functional bleb area in the MMC and Gel-Exo-siEN1 groups was greater than that in the control group, with the Gel-Exo-siEN1 group showing a slightly larger area than the MMC group (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>B). The reduction in IOP in the Gel-Exo-siEN1 group was comparable with that in the MMC group (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>C), indicating that Gel-Exo-siEN1 may improve postoperative bleb vascularization and prolong survival time. Hematoxylin and eosin and Masson's staining of conjunctival tissues showed that the Gel-Exo-siEN1 group significantly reduced collagen fiber deposition, with a looser tissue structure and decreased inflammatory cell infiltration compared with the control group (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>D). Immunofluorescence results (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>E) revealed higher expression levels of fibrosis-related genes collagen I and α-SMA in the control group, which were reduced in the Gel-Exo-siEN1 group. These findings suggested that Gel-Exo-siEN1 effectively inhibits scar formation after GFS, demonstrating antifibrotic effects comparable with MMC.</p><fig position="float" id="fig9" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Observation of the morphology of rat filtration vesicles using a slit lamp. (<bold>B</bold>) Analysis and comparison of the area of filtration vesicles in rats of different treatment groups. (<bold>C</bold>) Recording of IOP changes in rats of each treatment group at 14 days postoperatively. (<bold>D</bold>) Masson and hematoxylin and eosin staining of conjunctival tissues of the operated area to assess the tissue condition. (<bold>E</bold>) Detection of the expression levels of The expression levels of collagen I and α-SMA were detected by immunofluorescence staining to assess fibrosis. <italic toggle="yes">Scale bar</italic>, 100 µm. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 8. ns, not significant. **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="iovs-67-2-18-f009.jpg"><?image-name iovs-67-2-18-f009.jpg?><?image-size 316267?><?image-md5 f1e7d6ca04fc6997bc2751e701ffc149?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 2181?><?image-original-width 1500?><?image-scaled-height 1091?><?image-scaled-width 750?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/dfb8/12889168/f1e7d6ca04fc/iovs-67-2-18-f009.jpg?><?thumb-name iovs-67-2-18-f009.gif?><?thumb-size 10911?><?thumb-md5 ccd3f15e2347288e8dad00e5bcdb1f24?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 145?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/dfb8/12889168/ccd3f15e2347/iovs-67-2-18-f009.gif?></graphic></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4"><title>Discussion</title><p>After glaucoma filtration, incision of the conjunctiva and its underlying tissues initiates the release of inflammation-inducing factors, including neutrophils and macrophages, thereby triggering the activation of HTFs. This activation results in heightened proliferation and increased synthesis of fibrotic proteins, ultimately leading to the development of excessive scar tissue in the follicular region.<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> Specifically, TGF-β2 is the predominant isoform in ocular tissues, particularly linked to conjunctival scarring and fibrosis.<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> Therefore, this study used TGF-β2 to induce fibrotic processes in primary HTFs cultured in vitro, establishing an in vitro model of fibrosis.</p><p>The homeobox protein transcription factor EN1 is crucial for nervous system development and differentiation.<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> Recent studies show that blocking EN1 in fibroblasts can lead to scarless skin wound healing.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> Our research revealed that TGF-β2 stimulation of HTF increased EN1 expression, which was also elevated in conjunctival scar tissues after rat filtration surgery. Suppressing EN1 with siRNA reversed TGF-β2–induced increases in fibrosis-related genes (α-SMA, collagen I, and FN). Transcriptome sequencing of siEN1-transfected HTFs stimulated with TGF-β2 showed differentially expressed mRNAs enriched in ECM components. KEGG pathway analysis highlighted ECM–receptor interaction pathways. These findings suggested EN1's role in ECM organization and fibrosis pathogenesis. Previous studies confirm that EN1 activates fibroblasts, enhancing their response to TGF-β1/2, increasing ECM protein production, myofibroblast differentiation, and collagen release.<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> In synovial samples from patients with joint fibrosis, EN1 was notably activated in fibroblasts. Coexpression analysis showed significant overlap with COL1A1, highlighting EN1 as a key transcription factor linked to disease severity and prognosis.<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> Our research showed that downregulating EN1 inhibits TGF-β2–induced HTF proliferation, myofibroblast transition, and ECM synthesis, suggesting EN1 siRNA's therapeutic potential for preventing filtration bleb scarring. Using the JASPAR database, we identified EN1-binding sites in the promoters of fibrosis-related genes FN, collagen I, and α-SMA, validated by dual-luciferase reporter assay. EN1 likely directly regulates these genes. Future research will integrate transcriptome and ChIP-seq data to explore EN1's regulatory influence on fibrosis-related genes and downstream pathways, aiming to clarify EN1's role in fibrosis regulation.</p><p>YAP/TAZ, the main downstream effector of the Hippo pathway, regulates fibroblast activation and matrix formation and reflects cellular responses to ECM mechanical signals.<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref><sup>–</sup><xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> Studies have found that inhibiting the YAP signal during wound healing can prevent EN1 activation, thereby promoting wound repair mediated by EN1 cells without fibrosis.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> Therefore, the YAP pathway may be an upstream related mechanism for inhibiting fibrosis. We also demonstrated through experiments such as ChIP-PCR that the YAP/TAZ pathway might promote TGF-β2–induced upregulation of EN1 expression in HTFs in an SMAD3-dependent manner. We hypothesized that, after TGF-β2 stimulation, it might directly activate or indirectly activate the YAP/TAZ pathway in a classical manner, leading to increased SMAD3 expression. The elevated SMAD3 protein can then directly bind to the promoter region of the EN1 protein, mediating the expression of the EN1 gene. In future studies, we will explore this mechanism further. Therefore, we propose that EN1 may play a critical role in postoperative conjunctival fibrosis after GFS, and its underlying mechanism will be further investigated in future studies. In the present study, we examined EN1 function using a TGF-β2–driven model of fibrosis. However, bleb scarring after GFS is a multifactorial process, and our findings primarily reflect EN1’s mechanistic role under TGF-β2–dominant conditions, without accounting for the contributions of other fibrotic signals. Future studies will investigate EN1 regulation within a complex fibrotic microenvironment to achieve a more comprehensive understanding of its potential in mitigating postoperative bleb fibrosis.</p><p>Given the ocular phototoxicity of the YAP pathway inhibitor verteporfin, hindering its practical application, we turned to EN1 as the therapeutic focus. siRNA can specifically bind to and promote the degradation of target mRNA or block its translation, effectively reducing the production of specific proteins. This mechanism can precisely target pathological genes, prevent the formation of harmful proteins, and achieve therapeutic purposes. This technology has shown therapeutic potential in the fields of genetic diseases, cancer, and viral diseases.<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> In our in vitro studies, we also found that EN1 siRNA can effectively inhibit the expression of EN1 in HTFs, thereby resisting TGF-β2–induced HTFs fibrosis. Considering the genetic differences between species, we rescreened specific siRNAs that can effectively inhibit EN1 expression in rat Tenon capsule fibroblasts, providing a foundation for the subsequent synthesis of Gel-Exo-siEN1 and its application in in vivo experiments.</p><p>A major challenge for in vivo siRNA therapy is efficient delivery to target cells. Novel delivery systems, including Exos—natural phospholipid vesicles with high biocompatibility—protect siRNA, enhance its stability, and facilitate cell membrane penetration while avoiding clearance by the reticuloendothelial system.<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> Exos have been studied extensively as therapeutic siRNA carriers, particularly in vivo. For example, Exos from mouse dendritic cells successfully delivered siRNA targeting BACE-1 to the brain for gene therapy.<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> Exos have also delivered mu-opioid receptor siRNA to the central nervous system to treat morphine addiction and treat ocular diseases by delivering various siRNAs or microRNAs to affected areas of the eyes.<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> Using Exos as carriers for EN1 siRNA shows promise, particularly Exos from HEK-293 cells selected for their low immunogenicity. Successful encapsulation of siEN1 within Exos was confirmed through experiments such as flow cytometry and confocal fluorescence, enabling further researches. In previous studies, Exos were primarily administered via intravenous or local injections. Although these methods generated significant research outcomes, they encountered limitations such as the need for repeated injections, low retention efficiency in targeted therapy, short duration of effectiveness, and immune clearance issues.<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref><sup>–</sup><xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> However, the healing process after GFS is protracted, spanning from the early postoperative period to peaking in the subsequent weeks and declining by the second or third months after surgery.<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref> Thus, after successfully developing Exos loaded with EN1 siRNA, a critical concern was reducing the injection frequency to achieve efficient delivery, prolonging their in vivo efficacy, and ensuring sustained therapeutic effects of EN1 siRNA. In recent years, combining Exos with biomaterials has emerged as a promising strategy in regenerative medicine. GelMA, derived from methacrylation-modified gelatin, has been used extensively in tissue engineering owing to its excellent biocompatibility and tunable mechanical properties resembling the natural ECM.<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> GelMA-based hydrogels serve as optimal Exo carriers, demonstrating significant potential across various domains.<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref><sup>–</sup><xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref> Our preliminary investigations used GelMA combined with oxidized dextran to create GelDex, a photo-cross-linkable bioadhesive hydrogel loaded with nucleic acid aptamers targeting TβR II receptors, enabling sustained release of nucleic acid aptamers.<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref> Building on this groundwork, we functionalized GelMA hydrogel with Gel-Exo-siEN1, which reduced Exo clearance and enabled sustained release of antifibrotic siEN1. In vitro, Gel-Exo-siEN1 showed excellent biocompatibility, was internalized by rat Tenon's fibroblasts, inhibited EN1 expression, suppressed TGF-β2–induced proliferation and migration, and reduced fibrosis-related gene expression. In vivo, 14 days after GFS, Gel-Exo-siEN1 decreased inflammation, cell proliferation, collagen I and α-SMA expression, and collagen deposition and significantly prolonged filtering bleb survival. Its antifibrotic effects were comparable with MMC without notable side effects. Future studies will extend postoperative observation to assess long-term safety and filtering bleb function. In summary, Gel-Exo-siEN1 hydrogel effectively inhibits EN1 expression and exerts strong antifibrotic effects both in vitro and in vivo.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="iovs-67-2-18_s001" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplement 1</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="iovs-67-2-18_s001.docx" id="d67e883" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><?suppdata-name iovs-67-2-18_s001.docx?><?suppdata-size 1606292?><?suppdata-md5 b77dfcc551172d01e494003bcf71f95a?><?suppdata-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?suppdata-mime-type application?><?suppdata-mime-sub-type vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document?><?suppdata-cloudpmc-urn urn:app:dfb8/12889168/b77dfcc55117/iovs-67-2-18_s001.docx?></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="iovs-67-2-18_s002" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplement 2</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="iovs-67-2-18_s002.docx" id="d67e887" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><?suppdata-name iovs-67-2-18_s002.docx?><?suppdata-size 16298?><?suppdata-md5 cd3a5bf9fe11d638e1c43ca3334d3961?><?suppdata-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?suppdata-mime-type application?><?suppdata-mime-sub-type vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document?><?suppdata-cloudpmc-urn urn:app:dfb8/12889168/cd3a5bf9fe11/iovs-67-2-18_s002.docx?></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>Supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 82571207); Chongqing Talents Program Project (CSTC2022YCJH-BGZXM0163);Innovation and Development Joint Fund Project of Chongqing Natural Science Foundation (CSTB2024NSCQ-LZX0023).</p><p>
<bold>Author Contributions:</bold> L.Y. performed the experiments and wrote the manuscript; L.W.D. contributed to the analysis of the data; ZXM collected the clinical samples; Y.J.L. and L.X.J. reviewed the manuscript; X.L. is the guarantor of this work and, as such, had full access to all the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p><p>
<bold>Ethics Approval and Consent to Participate:</bold> Ethics approval Animal protocols were approved by the Committee on the Ethics of Animal Experiments of Chongqing Medical University.</p><p>
<bold>Data Availability:</bold> All data are available from the corresponding authors upon reasonable request.</p><p content-type="COI-statement">Disclosure: <bold>Y. Lin</bold>, None; <bold>W. Luo</bold>, None; <bold>X. Zhu</bold>, None; <bold>J. Yu</bold>, None; <bold>X. Li</bold>, None; <bold>L. Xie</bold>, None</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Stein</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khawaja</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Weizer</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Glaucoma in adults-screening, diagnosis, and management: a review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>; <volume>325</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>164</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33433580</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2020.21899</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wiggs</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aung</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khawaja</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khor</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The genetic basis for adult onset glaucoma: recent advances and future directions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Prog Retin Eye Res</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>; <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>101066</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35589495</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.preteyeres.2022.101066</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>DY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname>
<given-names>WH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<article-title>The critical role of the conjunctiva in glaucoma filtration surgery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Prog Retin Eye Res</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>28</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>303</fpage>–<lpage>328</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19573620</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.preteyeres.2009.06.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Cabourne</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname>
<given-names>JCK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schlottmann</surname>
<given-names>PG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Mitomycin C versus 5-fluorouracil for wound healing in glaucoma surgery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cochrane Database Syst Rev</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>2015</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>CD006259</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26545176</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD006259.pub2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8763343</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Beltran</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Graves</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Blancafort</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Novel role of Engrailed 1 as a prosurvival transcription factor in basal-like breast cancer and engineering of interference peptides block its oncogenic function</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Oncogene</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>33</volume>(<issue>39</issue>): <fpage>4767</fpage>–<lpage>4777</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24141779</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/onc.2013.422</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4184217</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>YJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sung</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<article-title>Engrailed 1 overexpression as a potential prognostic marker in quintuple-negative breast cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cancer Biol Ther</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>; <volume>19</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>345</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29333926</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/15384047.2018.1423913</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5902237</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Mascharak</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>DesJardins-Park</surname>
<given-names>HE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Davitt</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<article-title>Preventing Engrailed-1 activation in fibroblasts yields wound regeneration without scarring</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Science</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>; <volume>372</volume>(<issue>6540</issue>): <fpage>eaba2374</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33888614</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.aba2374</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9008875</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Correa-Gallegos</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Christ</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<article-title>Two succeeding fibroblastic lineages drive dermal development and the transition from regeneration to scarring</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Cell Biol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>; <volume>20</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>422</fpage>–<lpage>431</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29593327</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41556-018-0073-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Cui</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<article-title>A bone-targeted engineered exosome platform delivering siRNA to treat osteoporosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Bioact Mater</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34901540</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bioactmat.2021.09.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8636739</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Alvarez-Erviti</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Seow</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Betts</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lakhal</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname>
<given-names>MJA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Delivery of siRNA to the mouse brain by systemic injection of targeted exosomes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Biotechnol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>29</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>341</fpage>–<lpage>345</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21423189</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nbt.1807</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Nakamura-Shibasaki</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Takenaka</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chikama</surname>
<given-names>TI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sonoda</surname>
<given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kiuchi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Matrix metalloproteinase and cytokine expression in Tenon fibroblasts during scar formation after glaucoma filtration or implant surgery in rats</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cell Biochem Funct</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>31</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>482</fpage>–<lpage>488</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23086831</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cbf.2923</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Human umbilical cord mesenchymal stem cell-derived exosomes combined with gelatin methacryloyl hydrogel to promote fractional laser injury wound healing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int Wound J</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>; <volume>20</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>4040</fpage>–<lpage>4049</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37429607</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/iwj.14295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10681517</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC12007967"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<article-title>Evaluation of chitosan/aptamer targeting TGF-β receptor II thermo-sensitive gel for scarring in rat glaucoma filtration surgery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>56</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>5465</fpage>–<lpage>5476</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26284552</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1167/iovs.15-16683</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Masoumpour</surname>
<given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nowroozzadeh</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Razeghinejad</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Current and future techniques in wound healing modulation after glaucoma filtering surgeries</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Open Ophthalmol J</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27014389</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2174/1874364101610010068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4780518</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Cordeiro</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Role of transforming growth factor beta in conjunctival scarring</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Sci (Lond)</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>104</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>187</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12546640</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1042/CS20020150</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Cai</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<article-title>Tetramethylpyrazine attenuates transdifferentiation of TGF-β2-treated human Tenon's fibroblasts</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>; <volume>57</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>4740</fpage>–<lpage>4748</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27607420</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1167/iovs.16-19529</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>McGrath</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Michael</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pandha</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Engrailed homeobox transcription factors as potential markers and targets in cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">FEBS Lett</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>587</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>549</fpage>–<lpage>554</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23395604</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.febslet.2013.01.054</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Györfi</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Matei</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fuchs</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<article-title>Engrailed 1 coordinates cytoskeletal reorganization to induce myofibroblast differentiation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Exp Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>; <volume>218</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>e20201916</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34259830</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1084/jem.20201916</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8288503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Ng</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>D'Agostino</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<article-title>Interleukin-11 is a therapeutic target in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Transl Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>; <volume>11</volume>(<issue>511</issue>): <fpage>eaaw1237</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31554736</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/scitranslmed.aaw1237</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<article-title>Single-cell and bulk tissue sequencing unravels the heterogeneity of synovial microenvironment in arthrofibrosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">iScience</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>; <volume>26</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>107379</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37705954</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.isci.2023.107379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10495645</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lagares</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<article-title>Mechanosignaling through YAP and TAZ drives fibroblast activation and fibrosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>308</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>L344</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25502501</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/ajplung.00300.2014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4329470</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Attisano</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wrana</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Signal integration in TGF-β, WNT, and Hippo pathways</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">F1000Prime Rep</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23755364</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.12703/P5-17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3672943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Futakuchi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Inoue</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>FY</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<article-title>YAP/TAZ are essential for TGF-β2-mediated conjunctival fibrosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>; <volume>59</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>3069</fpage>–<lpage>3078</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30025139</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1167/iovs.18-24258</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bahal</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rasmussen</surname>
<given-names>TP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Manautou</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname>
<given-names>XB</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The growth of siRNA-based therapeutics: updated clinical studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biochem Pharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>; <volume>189</volume>: <fpage>114432</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33513339</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bcp.2021.114432</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8187268</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Friedrich</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aigner</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Therapeutic siRNA: state-of-the-art and future perspectives</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BioDrugs</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>; <volume>36</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>549</fpage>–<lpage>571</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35997897</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40259-022-00549-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9396607</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Tai</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Corey</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A ribonucleoprotein octamer for targeted siRNA delivery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Biomed Eng</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>; <volume>2</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>326</fpage>–<lpage>337</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30936447</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41551-018-0214-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6136846</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A window onto siRNA delivery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Biotechnol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>31</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>611</fpage>–<lpage>612</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23839146</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nbt.2634</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<article-title>Targeted exosome-mediated delivery of opioid receptor Mu siRNA for the treatment of morphine relapse</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>17543</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26633001</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/srep17543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4668387</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Hua</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<article-title>Huc-MSCs-derived exosomes attenuate inflammatory pain by regulating microglia pyroptosis and autophagy via the miR-146a-5p/TRAF6 axis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Nanobiotechnology</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>; <volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>324</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35836229</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12951-022-01522-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9281091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>ZM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<article-title>Macrophage-derived exosomal Mir-155 regulating cardiomyocyte pyroptosis and hypertrophy in uremic cardiomyopathy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JACC Basic to Transl Sci</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>; <volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>148</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jacbts.2019.10.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7046511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32140622</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<article-title>Large-scale generation of functional mRNA-encapsulating exosomes via cellular nanoporation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Biomed Eng</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>; <volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31844155</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41551-019-0485-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7080209</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<article-title>Investigation on novel chitosan nanoparticle-aptamer complexes targeting TGF-β receptor II</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Pharm</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>456</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>499</fpage>–<lpage>507</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23999222</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijpharm.2013.08.028</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Yue</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Trujillo-de Santiago</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tamayol</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Annabi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khademhosseini</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Synthesis, properties, and biomedical applications of gelatin methacryloyl (GelMA) hydrogels</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biomaterials</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>254</fpage>–<lpage>271</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26414409</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2015.08.045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4610009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Kurian</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname>
<given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>KD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>HW</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Multifunctional GelMA platforms with nanomaterials for advanced tissue therapeutics</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Bioact Mater</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>295</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34541401</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bioactmat.2021.06.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8424393</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<article-title>Bone mesenchymal stem cell-derived exosome-loaded injectable hydrogel for minimally invasive treatment of spinal cord injury</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nanomedicine (Lond)</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>; <volume>16</volume>(<issue>18</issue>): <fpage>1567</fpage>–<lpage>1579</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34189939</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2217/nnm-2021-0025</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lei</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Nano-micron combined hydrogel microspheres: novel answer for minimal invasive biomedical applications</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Macromol Rapid Commun</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>; <volume>45</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>e2300670</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38400695</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/marc.202300670</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<article-title>The effect of GelDex-S58 hydrogel on anti-conjunctival scarring after glaucoma filtration surgery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">iScience</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>; <volume>26</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>107633</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37664639</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.isci.2023.107633</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10474451</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>