<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1685</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jtd</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Thoracic Disease</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title>J Thorac Dis</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group><publisher><publisher-name>AME Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12268815</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12268815</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12268815</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40688308</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/jtd-2025-1088</article-id><title-group><article-title><italic>TIMP1</italic> regulation of cardiac fibroblast proliferation via the TGF-β/Smad pathway in an <italic>in vitro</italic> model of atrial fibrillation</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="author"><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yimeng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref rid="afn2" ref-type="author-notes">#</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="L">Lianzhi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref rid="afn2" ref-type="author-notes">#</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="W">Wenjia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qunlin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names initials="N">Nan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson-Smith</surname><given-names initials="AR">Ashley R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="N">Nannan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_fncrsp93pmc__">✉</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Cardiology, Yangpu Hospital, School of Medicine, Tongji University, Shanghai, China;</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Faculty of Medicine and Health, The University of Sydney, Sydney, Australia</aff><author-notes><fn id="afn1"><p><italic>Contributions:</italic> (I) Conception and design: Y Zhou, L Zhang, N Chen; (II) Administrative support: W Zhang, N Xu; (III) Provision of study materials or patients: Q Gong, Z Zhang; (IV) Collection and assembly of data: Y Zhou, W Zhang; (V) Data analysis and interpretation: L Zhang, Q Gong, N Chen; (VI) Manuscript writing: All authors; (VII) Final approval of manuscript: All authors.</p></fn><fn id="afn2"><label>#</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn><fn id="cor1"><label>✉</label><p><italic>Correspondence to:</italic> Nannan Chen, MD. Department of Cardiology, Yangpu Hospital, School of Medicine, Tongji University, No. 450 Tengyue Road, Yangpu District, Shanghai 200090, China. Email: <email>chennannan@sina.com</email>.</p></fn><fn id="_fncrsp93pmc__"><label>✉</label><p>Corresponding author.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>4249</fpage><page-range>4249–4263</page-range><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>18</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2025 AME Publishing Company. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><license><license-p><italic>Open Access Statement:</italic> This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 4.0 International License (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0), which permits the non-commercial replication and distribution of the article with the strict proviso that no changes or edits are made and the original work is properly cited (including links to both the formal publication through the relevant DOI and the license). See: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jtd-17-06-4249.pdf" content-type="pmc-pdf"><?cloudpmc-path 29d6/12268815/86b4a5e3605d/jtd-17-06-4249.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 2080149?></self-uri><abstract id="abstract1"><title>Abstract</title><sec id="sec1" disp-level="2"><title>Background</title><p>Atrial fibrillation (AF) is closely associated with atrial fibrosis and is primarily driven by cardiac fibroblast-mediated extracellular matrix (ECM) production. Tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinases-1 (<italic>TIMP1</italic>), a key ECM regulator, has been implicated in cardiovascular fibrosis, but its role in AF remains unclear. This study examined the function of <italic>TIMP1 </italic>in the angiotensin II (ang II)-induced activation of rat cardiac fibroblasts.</p></sec><sec id="sec2" disp-level="2"><title>Methods</title><p>Differentially expressed gene (DEG) and functional enrichment analyses were performed using the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE115574" ext-link-type="uri">GSE115574</ext-link> dataset. Key gene modules were identified via protein-protein interaction (PPI) network analysis, and critical module intersection gene expression was analyzed in AF samples from the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE115574" ext-link-type="uri">GSE115574</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE14975" ext-link-type="uri">GSE14975</ext-link> datasets. Different concentrations and times of ang II administration were used to treat rat cardiac fibroblasts to mimic AF pathology, and their effects on <italic>TIMP1</italic> expression and ang II-induced proliferation and related fibrosis pathways were investigated via transfection, quantitative polymerase chain reaction, Western blotting (WB), and Cell Counting Kit-8 (CCK-8), and colony formation assays.</p></sec><sec id="sec3" disp-level="2"><title>Results</title><p>Functional enrichment analysis showed that DEGs were enriched in collagen fibrillar organization and ECM-receptor interactions. Seven essential intersecting genes (<italic>BGN</italic>, <italic>COL1A1</italic>, <italic>COL1A2</italic>, <italic>COL3A1</italic>, <italic>FMOD</italic>, <italic>THBS2</italic>, and <italic>TIMP1</italic>) identified from the PPI network analysis were highly expressed in AF samples from the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE115574" ext-link-type="uri">GSE115574</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE14975" ext-link-type="uri">GSE14975</ext-link> datasets.<italic> In vitro</italic> studies revealed ang II-induced upregulation of <italic>TIMP1</italic> expression and activation of the TGF-β/Smad pathway. Knockdown of <italic>TIMP1</italic> enhanced ang II-induced proliferation of rat cardiac fibroblasts and upregulated the expression of fibrotic markers and proteins related to the TGF-β/Smad signaling pathway.</p></sec><sec id="sec4" disp-level="2"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Our study demonstrated that <italic>TIMP1</italic> regulates myocardial fibrosis through the TGF-β/Smad pathway, particularly affecting cardiac fibroblast proliferation. Our findings provide new insights into the molecular process of AF and may offer new targets for therapeutic strategies.</p></sec><sec id="kwd-group1" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Keywords: </bold> Tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinases-1 (<italic>TIMP1</italic>), atrial fibrillation (AF), TGF-β/Smad pathway, atrial fibrosis, angiotensin II (ang II)</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>status</meta-name><meta-value>released</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>display-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-journal-matter</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-scanned</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-retracted</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes notes-type="article-notes"><sec id="historyarticle-meta1" sec-type="history" disp-level="2"><p>Received 2025 May 27; Accepted 2025 Jun 16; Issue date 2025 Jun 30.</p></sec></notes></front><body><boxed-text id="ba" position="float"><?disp-level 1?><caption><title>Highlight box</title></caption><sec id="sec5" disp-level="2"><title>Key findings</title><p>• Through bioinformatic analysis of public datasets, tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinases-1 (<italic>TIMP1</italic>) was identified as a hub gene highly expressed in atrial fibrillation (AF).</p><p>• Angiotensin II (ang II) upregulated <italic>TIMP1</italic> expression in rat cardiac fibroblasts and activated TGF-β/Smad pathway.</p><p>• <italic>TIMP1</italic> knockdown inhibited ang II-induced fibroblast proliferation and fibrosis marker expression, while overexpression had the opposite effect.</p></sec><sec id="sec6" disp-level="2"><title>What is known and what is new?</title><p>• Atrial fibrosis plays a central role in AF progression, and extracellular matrix remodeling contributes to fibrotic changes.</p><p>• This study demonstrates that <italic>TIMP1</italic> promotes ang II-induced cardiac fibroblast proliferation and fibrosis through the TGF-β/Smad pathway, revealing its potential as a novel target in AF.</p></sec><sec id="sec7" disp-level="2"><title>What is the implication, and what should change now?</title><p>• <italic>TIMP1</italic> is a key regulator of cardiac fibroblast activation and fibrosis in AF and may serve as a promising therapeutic target.</p><p>• Targeting <italic>TIMP1</italic> or its downstream pathways could help attenuate atrial structural remodeling and improve AF treatment strategies.</p></sec></boxed-text><sec id="sec8" disp-level="1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Atrial fibrillation (AF) is characterized by irregular and often rapid contractions of the atria (<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). It is commonly associated with cardiovascular disease, hypertension, and diabetes (<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). AF is a common disease worldwide, with its morbidity and mortality rates continuing to rise in recent years (<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). This condition can lead to various complications, such as thromboembolic stroke, heart failure, and other cardiovascular issues (<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Currently, the main treatment approaches for AF include pharmacotherapy, electrophysiological procedures, and surgical intervention, and are obviously not without potential adverse effects (<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). A study has suggested that fibrosis plays a crucial role in sustaining the re-entrant drivers that maintain arrhythmias (<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Therefore, a better understanding of preventing fibrosis could reveal new targets for innovative treatment strategies.</p><p>Angiotensin II (ang II) is a key mediator in the development of atrial fibrosis and AF. It has been shown to promote atrial remodeling by modulating ion channels and currents, leading to electrical and structural changes that increase the susceptibility to AF (<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Specifically, ang II activates the TGF-β1/Smad signaling pathway, which drives fibroblast proliferation and extracellular matrix (ECM) deposition, contributing to atrial fibrosis (<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Studies have demonstrated that ang II-induced fibrosis leads to increased atrial stiffness and conduction abnormalities, which are critical factors in the development and maintenance of AF. A recent study by Shi<italic> et al. </italic>showed that ang II infusion in mice resulted in significant atrial fibrosis and increased AF vulnerability, highlighting the role of ang II in AF pathogenesis (<xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Another study demonstrated that the administration of the PGI2 analog iloprost inhibited ang II-induced atrial fibrosis and reduced AF inducibility in a mouse model (<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). These findings underscore the importance of ang II in driving atrial fibrosis and AF. Therefore, we simulated AF by treating cells with ang II.</p><p>AF is closely related to atrial fibrosis, which as an alteration of atrial tissue structure, may lead to electrical conduction abnormalities through the remodeling of the ECM, contributing to AF onset and persistence (<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinases-1 (<italic>TIMP1</italic>), a member of the <italic>TIMP</italic> family of proteins, is essential for controlling the activity of matrix metalloproteinases (MMPs). The ECM, a complex network of proteins providing structural support to cells, is targeted by MMPs, which break it down. <italic>TIMP1</italic> is an inhibitor that binds to MMPs, modulating their activity and preventing excessive ECM degradation (<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). It impacts numerous physiological processes, including immune response, wound healing, and tissue remodeling. Additionally, <italic>TIMP1</italic> has been linked to pathological disorders such as cancer, fibrosis, and cardiovascular illnesses, in which dysregulation of matrix remodeling processes occurs (<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Several studies have examined the impact of <italic>TIMP1</italic> on patients with AF. Li<italic> et al. </italic>discovered that patients with AF who had higher serum levels of <italic>TIMP1</italic> before radiofrequency ablation therapy were at a significantly increased risk of experiencing a recurrence of AF post-treatment, notably when TIMP1 levels surpassed 124.15 ng/mL (<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Sun<italic> et al. </italic>also reported that higher serum levels of<italic> TIMP1</italic> in patients with AF may predict increased atrial fibrosis and be an independent predictor of AF recurrence after radiofrequency ablation therapy (<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Fragão-Marques<italic> et al.</italic>’s research indicated an elevated production of collagen III and atrial fibrosis in AF patients with severe aortic stenosis, characterized by ECM remodeling and a decreased <italic>MMP16/TIMP4</italic> ratio (<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Additionally, these patients exhibited elevated serum levels of <italic>TIMP1</italic> and <italic>TIMP2</italic> proteins. Therefore, clarifying the role of <italic>TIMP1</italic> in inflammation and fibrosis is crucial for understanding its impact on patients with AF.</p><p>This work aimed to delineate the regulatory processes of <italic>TIMP1</italic> in the pathophysiology of AF and to assess its potential as a therapeutic target. We used bioinformatics to examine<italic> TIMP1</italic> expression in AF samples from the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE115574" ext-link-type="uri">GSE115574</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE14975" ext-link-type="uri">GSE14975</ext-link> datasets. <italic>In vitro </italic>research was conducted to determine the influence of ang II on <italic>TIMP1</italic> expression in rat cardiac fibroblasts and to evaluate its subsequent effects on fibrosis signaling pathways. Furthermore, we investigated the impact of <italic>TIMP1</italic> expression regulation on fibrosis marker expression and cell proliferation, with the aim of discovering novel intervention strategies for AF. We present this article in accordance with the MDAR reporting checklist (available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://jtd.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/jtd-2025-1088/rc" ext-link-type="uri">https://jtd.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/jtd-2025-1088/rc</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="sec9" disp-level="1"><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec10" disp-level="2"><title>Data sources and collection</title><p>The AF-related datasets (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE115574" ext-link-type="uri">GSE115574</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE14975" ext-link-type="uri">GSE14975</ext-link>) were obtained from the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) public repository (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</ext-link>). The <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE115574" ext-link-type="uri">GSE115574</ext-link> dataset consists of 28 sinus rhythm (SR) samples, regarded as the normal group, and 31 permanent AF samples, deemed the AF group. The <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE14975" ext-link-type="uri">GSE14975</ext-link> dataset includes 5 AF samples and 5 SR samples, with the former being the AF group and the latter the normal group.</p></sec><sec id="sec11" disp-level="2"><title>Screening and functional enrichment analysis of differentially expressed genes (DEGs)</title><p>Using the GEO2R tool (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/geo2r/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/geo2r/</ext-link>), we analyzed the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE115574" ext-link-type="uri">GSE115574</ext-link> dataset to identify the DEGs. When conducting AF-related gene expression studies, we referenced the fold change (FC) thresholds used in a similar study (<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) to ensure that our screening criteria captured the biologically meaningful gene expression changes. Our goal was to select genes with sufficiently significant changes that could potentially impact the pathological process of AF while avoiding false-positive results due to noise. We also cross-validated the expression of critical genes through the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE14975" ext-link-type="uri">GSE14975</ext-link> dataset to ensure the reproducibility and reliability of our results. Our study selected DEGs based on their expression differences between AF and standard SR samples. We set the FC threshold for upregulated DEGs to be greater than 1.3 and that for downregulated DEGs to be less than 0.77. In addition, we used a P value of less than 0.05 as the significance criterion to further ensure that the expression changes of the selected genes were statistically significant. The identified DEGs were submitted to the Database for Annotation, Visualization, and Integrated Discovery (DAVID; <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://david.ncifcrf.gov/" ext-link-type="uri">https://david.ncifcrf.gov/</ext-link>) for functional enrichment analysis. Extensive investigations were conducted using Gene Ontology (GO) and the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) pathways to reveal related functions and pathways. Only findings with P values less than 0.05 were considered significant.</p></sec><sec id="sec12" disp-level="2"><title>Protein-protein interaction (PPI) network analysis and critical gene identification</title><p>After identifying 224 DEGs, we used Cytoscape software (version 3.8.0) to construct a PPI network of the proteins encoded by these DEGs. The Cytohubba plugin within Cytoscape was then employed to identify three key network modules through algorithms including maximum clique centrality (MCC), degree, and maximum neighborhood component (MNC). We performed intersection analysis using the online tool provided by Bioinformatics &amp; Evolutionary Genomics (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.psb.ugent.be/webtools/Venn/" ext-link-type="uri">http://bioinformatics.psb.ugent.be/webtools/Venn/</ext-link>) to obtain essential intersection genes. Following this, we analyzed the expression of these intersection genes in AF samples from both the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE115574" ext-link-type="uri">GSE115574</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE14975" ext-link-type="uri">GSE14975</ext-link> datasets, comparing their expression differences between the AF and SR samples.</p></sec><sec id="sec13" disp-level="2"><title>Ethical statement</title><p>The study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki and its subsequent amendments. The data used in this study were obtained from public databases (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE115574" ext-link-type="uri">GSE115574</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE14975" ext-link-type="uri">GSE14975</ext-link>), which contain anonymized human samples. No additional ethical approval was required for the use of these publicly available datasets.</p></sec><sec id="sec14" disp-level="2"><title>Cell culture and treatment</title><p>Rat primary cardiac fibroblasts were purchased from Stemcell Biotechnology Co., Ltd. (cat. no. STM-CE-3303; Shanghai, China; <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.stemrecell.com/primary-cell-rat-fibroblast/cardiacmuscle.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.stemrecell.com/primary-cell-rat-fibroblast/cardiacmuscle.html</ext-link>). The cells (5×10<sup>5 </sup>cells per well) were cultured in Dulbecco’s Modified Eagle Medium (DMEM; Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA), supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) and 1× penicillin/streptomycin (Thermo Fisher Scientific). Culture conditions were maintained at 37 ℃ in a 5% CO<sub>2</sub> atmosphere. Additionally, we simulated AF pathological conditions by inducing rat cardiac fibroblasts with various concentrations of ang II (1 nM, 10 nM, 100 nM, and 1 µM) at different time points (12, 24, and 48 hours). The selection of these concentrations and time points was based on published studies (<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>) and our preliminary experimental validation, which confirmed that these conditions effectively induced significant biological responses in rat cardiac fibroblasts.</p></sec><sec id="sec15" disp-level="2"><title>Transfection assay</title><p>To further elucidate the role of <italic>TIMP1</italic> in AF pathology, we performed gene knockdown and overexpression assays. We used three distinct sequences of small interfering RNAs (siRNAs) to reduce the <italic>TIMP1</italic> expression levels specifically. The siRNA sequences are as follows: si-<italic>TIMP1</italic>-1, 5'-CAUCCUCUUUGUUGCUAUCAUUGAUA-3' (sense sequence) and 5'-UAUCAAUGAUAGCAACAAGAGGAUG-3' (antisense sequence); si-<italic>TIMP1</italic>-2, 5'-GCCGUUUUAAGGAACGGAAAUUUGCA-3' (sense sequence) and 5'-UGCAAAUUUUCCGUUUCCUUUAAACGGC-3' (antisense sequence); and si-<italic>TIMP1</italic>-3, 5'-GAAUCCAGAUUUGUGCACCUGGCAA-3' (sense sequence) and 5'-UUGCCAGGUGCACAAAUCUGGAUUC-3' (antisense sequence). Meanwhile, <italic>TIMP1</italic> overexpression was achieved through construction of an expression vector containing the full-length coding sequence of the <italic>TIMP1</italic> gene. We used a final siRNA concentration of 50 nM and a plasmid DNA concentration of 2 µg/mL during transfection. Following the manufacturer’s protocol, transfections were carried out using Lipofectamine 3000 reagent (Invitrogen, Thermo Fisher Scientific). After transfection, cells were incubated for 48 hours before subsequent assays and analyses were conducted, allowing for a sufficient amount of time for the optimal expression levels to be reached.</p></sec><sec id="sec16" disp-level="2"><title>Quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction assay</title><p>Following the manufacturer’s instructions, we isolated total RNA from rat cardiac fibroblasts using the TRIzol reagent (Thermo Fisher Scientific). Complementary DNA (cDNA) synthesis was performed using the PrimeScript RT kit (Takara Bio, Kusatsu, Japan). Quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) was performed as described in the article by Shahrajabian<italic> et al. </italic>(<xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). <italic>GAPDH</italic> served as the internal control for standardizing the amplification data. The primer sequences used are listed in <xref rid="t1" ref-type="table"><italic>Table 1</italic></xref>. Expression analysis was conducted using <italic>GAPDH</italic> as the internal control and the 2<sup>-ΔΔCT</sup> method.</p><table-wrap id="t1" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Primer sequences for qRT-PCR</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="22.67%" span="1"/><col width="25.77%" span="1"/><col width="51.56%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Target</th><th valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Direction</th><th valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>TIMP1</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5'-GAGACACGCTAGAGCAGATACC-3'</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5'-CCAGGTCCGAGTTGCAGAAA-3'</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Collagen I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5'-GGGCAAGACAGTCATCGAAT-3'</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5'-TTGGTTTTTGGTCACGTTCA-3'</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Collagen III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5'-AGGGCAGGGAACAACTGATG-3'</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5'-GGTCCCACATTGCACAAAGC-3'</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>α-SMA</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5'-GCTGGTGATGATGCTCCCA-3'</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5'-GCCCATTCCAACCATCACTCC-3'</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>GAPDH</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5'-CTCAGTTGCTGAGGAGTCCC-3'</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5'-ATTCGAGAGAAGGGAGGGCT-3'</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p25"><p>qRT-PCR, quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec17" disp-level="2"><title>Western blotting assay</title><p>Protein lysates from rat atrial fibroblasts were produced by adding protease and phosphatase inhibitors to RIPA lysis solution (Thermo Fisher Scientific). The protein content was determined using the BCA Protein Assay Kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific). Following this, sodium dodecyl sulfate–polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis-separated proteins equal portions were applied in equal portions to polyvinylidene fluoride membranes (Thermo Fisher Scientific). The membranes were then incubated with the following primary antibodies: TGF-β1 (1:1,000; cat. no. ab215715; Abcam, Cambridge, UK), TIMP1 (1:2,000; cat. no. 30869-1-AP; Proteintech, Rosemont, IL, USA), α-SMA (1:5,000; cat. no. 14395-1-AP; Proteintech), collagen I (1:5,000; cat. no. 66761-1-Ig; Proteintech), collagen III (1:1,000; cat. no. 22734-1-AP; Proteintech), Smad2/3 (1:1,000; cat. no. ab202445; Abcam), and p-Smad2/3 (1:1,000; cat. no. ab272332; Abcam). GAPDH was probed as a housekeeping protein using an antibody diluted at 1:10,000 (cat. no. ab125247; Abcam). After incubation with the primary antibody and subsequent washing with Tris-buffered saline with Tween20 (TBST), the membranes were incubated with horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated goat anti-rabbit IgG (1:1,000; cat. no. ab21058; Abcam) or goat anti-mouse IgG (1:5,000; cat. no. ab20272; Abcam) for 1 hour at room temperature. Chemiluminescent detection was performed using an enhanced chemiluminescence kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific), and signals were visualized and recorded with a chemiluminescence imaging system (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA, USA).</p></sec><sec id="sec18" disp-level="2"><title>Cell Counting Kit-8 (CCK-8) assay</title><p>CCK-8 assay was used to assess the vitality of rat cardiac fibroblasts. The cells were seeded into 96-well plates at a density of 5×10<sup>3</sup> cells per well and subjected to various treatments. Following a 48-hour incubation, 10 µL of CCK-8 solution was added to each well. Following this, the optical density at 450 nm was measured using a microplate reader to evaluate the viability of cell proliferation.</p></sec><sec id="sec19" disp-level="2"><title>Colony formation assay</title><p>A colony formation assay was performed using rat atrial fibroblasts to evaluate the effects of 1 µM of ang II treatment for 48 hours and transfection with TIMP1 overexpression plasmids and siRNAs. Posttreatment, cells were seeded in a six-well plate at a density of 5×10<sup>3</sup> cells per well and cultured at 37 ℃ in an atmosphere containing 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Subsequently, the fibroblasts were fixed with methanol 15 minutes after the treatment. They were then stained with alkaline nitro blue tetrazolium chloride for 30 minutes, and the formation of evident colonies was observed using a stereomicroscope (Olympus, Tokyo, Japan). Each colony was photographed, and the rate of clonogenic development was quantified.</p></sec><sec id="sec20" disp-level="2"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All experiments were performed three times in biological replicates, and the results are expressed as the mean ± standard deviation. Statistical analysis was carried out using R language packages (The R Foundation for Statistical Computing).</p><p>The Student<italic> t</italic>-test was used for pairwise comparisons, while one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA), followed by the Tukey post hoc test, was employed for multiple-group comparisons. Statistical significance was set at a level of P value &lt;0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec21" disp-level="1"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec22" disp-level="2"><title>Enrichment analysis of 224 DEGs in the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE115574" ext-link-type="uri">GSE115574</ext-link> dataset</title><p>The GEO2R tool identified 113 upregulated DEGs and 111 down-regulated DEGs from the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE115574" ext-link-type="uri">GSE115574</ext-link> dataset (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig"><italic>Figure 1A</italic></xref>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://cdn.amegroups.cn/static/public/JTD-2025-1088-Supplementary.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Table S1</ext-link>). Subsequently, functional enrichment analysis was performed on 224 DEGs. In GO terms (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig"><italic>Figure 1B</italic></xref>), we found that DEGs were significantly enriched in biological processes associated with ECM, particularly collagen fibril organization and ECM organization. These results highlight the critical role of the ECM in the structural integrity of the heart and its dysregulation in AF. In addition, response to fibroblast growth factor was also enriched, suggesting that growth factors may influence cell proliferation and differentiation and thus be involved in the pathogenesis of AF. Within cellular components (CC) terms (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig"><italic>Figure 1C</italic></xref>), the DEGs were predominantly associated with the collagen-containing ECM and microfibrils. This suggests the importance of collagen and microfibrillar structures in maintaining cardiac tissue architecture and that their dysregulation may lead to the fibrotic changes observed in AF. Molecular functional (MF) analyses revealed genes enriched in platelet-derived growth factor binding, titin binding, and kinase activity. These molecular functions are critical for cell signaling, cytoskeletal integrity, and enzyme activity, and their dysregulation may affect cellular processes in AF (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig"><italic>Figure 1D</italic></xref>). Moreover, the KEGG pathway analysis identified significant enrichment in the pathways of myocardial contraction, ECM-receptor interaction, and focal adhesion. These pathways are essential for cardiac function and the maintenance of tissue integrity. Their dysregulation may lead to the electrophysiological and structural remodeling observed in AF, thereby contributing to the pathophysiology of the disease (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig"><italic>Figure 1E</italic></xref>).</p><fig id="f1" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Differential expression and enrichment analysis of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE115574" ext-link-type="uri">GSE115574</ext-link> dataset. (A) Volcano plot showing the differential expression analysis of genes in the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE115574" ext-link-type="uri">GSE115574</ext-link> dataset. Upregulated DEGs (red) and downregulated DEGs (blue) are indicated by their log2 fold change and −log10 P value. The horizontal dotted line represents the threshold for significant differential expression. (B-D) GO analysis of DEGs in BP, CC, and MF. The x-axis represents the percentage of genes, the y-axis represents the enriched GO terms, and the bubble size corresponds to the number of genes associated with each term. (E) KEGG pathway enrichment analysis of DEGs. Each bubble represents a specific KEGG pathway. The y-axis represents the enriched pathways, the x-axis represents the proportion of genes, and the bubble size corresponds to the number of enriched genes in each pathway. Each experiment was performed with at least three biological replicates. BP, biological processes; CC, cellular components; DEG, differentially expressed genes; GO, Gene Ontology; KEGG, Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes; MF, molecular functions; Not sig, not significant.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="jtd-17-06-4249-f1.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/29d6/12268815/a51fdd32c71a/jtd-17-06-4249-f1.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1040?><?original-width 2024?><?scaled-height 346?><?scaled-width 674?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="jtd-17-06-4249-f1.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/29d6/12268815/457fb4b2c843/jtd-17-06-4249-f1.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="sec23" disp-level="2"><title>Identification of key intersection genes and expression analysis in AF samples</title><p>In this study, we comprehensively analyzed the proteins encoded by 224 DEGs using PPI networks. The MCC, MNC, and degree algorithms identified three key gene modules, each characterized by 10 nodes and 45, 39, and 38 edges, respectively (<xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig"><italic>Figure 2A-2C</italic></xref>). As depicted in <xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig"><italic>Figure 2D</italic></xref>, we screened 7 key intersecting genes from these modules. We then analyzed the expression of these intersecting genes—<italic>BGN</italic>, <italic>COL1A1</italic>, <italic>COL1A2</italic>,<italic> COL3A1</italic>, <italic>FMOD</italic>, <italic>THBS2</italic>, and<italic> TIMP1</italic>—in the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE115574" ext-link-type="uri">GSE115574</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE14975" ext-link-type="uri">GSE14975</ext-link> datasets. The results, presented in <xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig"><italic>Figure 2E,2F</italic></xref>, indicated that these 7 genes are highly expressed in AF samples, suggesting their potential role in the etiology of AF. Among these, <italic>TIMP1 </italic>was selected as the hub gene for further analysis.</p><fig id="f2" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>PPI network analysis and expression validation of intersection genes. (A) A PPI network module derived from the MCC algorithm consisting of 10 nodes and 45 edges. (B) A PPI network module generated with the MNC algorithm consisting of 10 nodes and 39 edges. (C) A PPI network module generated with the degree algorithm consisting of 10 nodes and 38 edges. (D) A Venn diagram showing the intersection of seven essential overlapping genes found in the three PPI network modules. (E,F) Box plots of the expression levels for <italic>BGN</italic>, <italic>COL1A1</italic>, <italic>COL1A2</italic>, <italic>COL3A1</italic>, <italic>FMOD</italic>, <italic>THBS2</italic>, and <italic>TIMP1</italic> in the (E) <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE115574" ext-link-type="uri">GSE115574</ext-link> and (F) <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE14975" ext-link-type="uri">GSE14975</ext-link> samples, with the center line in each box indicating the median. Each experiment was performed with at least three biological replicates. *, P&lt;0.05; **, P&lt;0.01. AF, atrial fibrillation; MCC, maximum clique centrality; MNC, maximum neighborhood component; PPI, protein-protein interaction; <italic>TIMP1</italic>, tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinases-1.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="jtd-17-06-4249-f2.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/29d6/12268815/26c89f0a9bdd/jtd-17-06-4249-f2.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1640?><?original-width 1880?><?scaled-height 656?><?scaled-width 752?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="jtd-17-06-4249-f2.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/29d6/12268815/09858a7ad27d/jtd-17-06-4249-f2.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="sec24" disp-level="2"><title>ang II induced the upregulation of rat cardiac fibroblasts’ expression of <italic>TIMP1</italic> and activated fibrotic signaling</title><p>We used qRT-PCR assay to analyze the expression of <italic>TIMP1</italic> in rat cardiac fibroblasts treated with ang II at various doses (1 nM, 10 nM, 100 nM, and 1 µM) and durations (12, 24, and 48 hours). Following 48 hours of treatment with 1 µM of ang II, we observed maximum messenger RNA (mRNA) expression of <italic>TIMP1</italic>, which increased in a dose- and time-dependent manner (<xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig"><italic>Figure 3A,3B</italic></xref>).</p><fig id="f3" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Effect of ang II on the expression of <italic>TIMP1</italic>, TGF-β/Smad pathway-related proteins, and α-SMA. (A) qRT-PCR was performed to assess the mRNA expression levels of <italic>TIMP1</italic> in rat cardiac fibroblasts treated with different concentrations of ang II (1 nM, 10 nM, 100 nM, and 1 μM). (B) qRT-PCR was also performed to assess the mRNA expression levels of <italic>TIMP1</italic> in rat atrial fibroblasts subjected to different durations of 1 μM of ang II treatment (12, 24, and 48 hours). (C) WB was used to detect the expression of TGF-β1, p-Smad2, p-Smad3, Smad2, Smad3 and α-SMA after 48 hours of treatment with 1 μM of ang II. (D) The results of WB analysis for the same proteins are shown. Each experiment was performed with at least three biological replicates. *, P&lt;0.05. <italic>TIMP1</italic>, tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinases-1; ang II, angiotensin II; mRNA, messenger RNA; qRT-PCR, quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction; WB, Western blotting.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="jtd-17-06-4249-f3.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/29d6/12268815/0f3fb539b81a/jtd-17-06-4249-f3.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1120?><?original-width 1512?><?scaled-height 560?><?scaled-width 756?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="jtd-17-06-4249-f3.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/29d6/12268815/ea19203add1c/jtd-17-06-4249-f3.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p>Western blotting analysis showed significant upregulation of TGF-β1, α-SMA, p-Smad3, and p-Smad2 in cells treated with 1 µM of ang II for 48 hours (<xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig"><italic>Figure 3C,3D</italic></xref>). Notably, the non-phosphorylated forms of Smad2 and Smad3 did not exhibit significant changes upon ang II treatment. These findings suggest a potential mechanistic link between ang II stimulation and the activation of fibrotic signaling pathways in AF, with <italic>TIMP1</italic> acting as a major mediator.</p></sec><sec id="sec25" disp-level="2"><title>Regulation of <italic>TIMP1</italic> expression affected the ang II-induced proliferation of rat atrial fibroblasts</title><p>We transfected ang II-induced rat atrial fibroblasts with plasmids designed for <italic>TIMP1</italic> knockdown and overexpression. <italic>TIMP1</italic> knockdown and overexpression efficiency were evaluated using qRT-PCR and Western blotting analysis (<xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig"><italic>Figure 4A-4D</italic></xref>). Among the siRNAs tested, si-<italic>TIMP1</italic>-1 demonstrated the best knockdown efficiency and was chosen for further study. Following 48 hours of treatment with 1 µM of ang II, we assessed <italic>TIMP1</italic> expression in atrial fibroblasts. As shown in <xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig"><italic>Figure 4E</italic></xref>, qRT-PCR analysis showed that <italic>TIMP1 </italic>expression increased with the addition of ang II, decreased with knockdown, and increased again after <italic>TIMP1</italic> overexpression. In addition, we evaluated the proliferation activity and colony formation of cardiac fibroblasts after different treatments via CCK-8 and colony formation assays. The results in <xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig"><italic>Figure 4F,4G</italic></xref> show that ang II treatment induced upregulation of cell viability and increased the colony number as compared with the control condition. Knockdown of<italic> TIMP1 </italic>resulted in decreased cell viability and colony number, while overexpression of <italic>TIMP1</italic> resulted in a significant increase of both indicators (<xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig"><italic>Figure 4F,4G</italic></xref>). These findings suggest that <italic>TIMP1</italic> regulates the effects of ang II on cardiac fibroblasts proliferation.</p><fig id="f4" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><italic>TIMP1</italic> modulation altered the ang II-mediated effects on rat atrial fibroblast viability and proliferation. (A,B) qRT-PCR and WB were used to detect the <italic>TIMP1</italic> knockdown efficiency in rat cardiac fibroblasts treated with 1 μM of ang I for 48 hours. (C,D) Evaluation of <italic>TIMP1</italic> overexpression efficiency in rat atrial fibroblasts after 48 hours of 1-μM ang II treatment. (E) qRT-PCR was used to detect the expression of <italic>TIMP1</italic> in cardiac fibroblasts treated with 1 μM of ang II for 48 hours following knockdown or overexpression of <italic>TIMP1</italic>. (F) Cell viability of rat cardiac fibroblasts was assessed by CCK-8 assay after treatment with 1 μM of ang II, either alone or in combination with negative control (NC), <italic>TIMP1</italic> knockdown (si-<italic>TIMP1</italic>-1), or <italic>TIMP1</italic> overexpression (over-<italic>TIMP1</italic>). (G) Colony formation assay results of rat cardiac fibroblasts treated with control, 1 μM of ang II alone, ang II combined with NC, si-<italic>TIMP1</italic>-1, or over-<italic>TIMP1</italic>. Observed using a stereomicroscope and photographed with a scanner. Each experiment was performed with at least three biological replicates. *, P&lt;0.05. <italic>TIMP1</italic>, tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinases-1; ang II, angiotensin II; CCK-8, Cell Counting Kit-8; qRT-PCR, quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction; WB, Western blotting.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="jtd-17-06-4249-f4.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/29d6/12268815/651fef46b665/jtd-17-06-4249-f4.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1888?><?original-width 1895?><?scaled-height 755?><?scaled-width 758?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="jtd-17-06-4249-f4.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/29d6/12268815/08896e380838/jtd-17-06-4249-f4.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="sec26" disp-level="2"><title><italic>TIMP1</italic> regulated the expression of fibrosis markers through the TGF-β/Smad pathway</title><p>Using qRT-PCR and Western blotting analyses, we assessed the relative quantities of fibrotic markers—collagen I, α-SMA, and collagen III—in atrial fibroblasts after a 48-hour treatment with 1 µM of ang II. This treatment led to elevated mRNA and protein expression levels of collagen I, α-SMA, and collagen III upon the addition of ang II. Notably, the highest expression levels were observed after <italic>TIMP1 </italic>overexpression. In contrast, <italic>TIMP1</italic> knockdown resulted in decreased expression of these markers (<xref rid="f5" ref-type="fig"><italic>Figure 5A-5C</italic></xref>). The Western blotting analysis of TGF-β1, phosphorylated Smad2/3 (p-Smad2/3), and total Smad2/3 further supported these findings (<xref rid="f5" ref-type="fig"><italic>Figure 5D,5E</italic></xref>). These results indicate that TIMP1 regulates the expression of fibrosis-related markers through the TGF-β/Smad signaling pathway, thereby influencing the fibrotic processes in cardiac fibroblasts.</p><fig id="f5" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Effects of <italic>TIMP1</italic> regulation on fibrosis marker expression and TGF-β/Smad signaling in ang II-induced rat cardiac fibroblasts. (A-C) The mRNA expression levels of fibrotic markers, <italic>collagen I</italic>, <italic>collagen III</italic>, and <italic>α-SMA</italic> in rat cardiac fibroblasts were analyzed via qRT-PCR and WB assay. The experimental groups of rat cardiac fibroblasts were as follows: control, 1 μM of ang II, 1 μM of ang II + NC, 1 μM of ang II + si-<italic>TIMP1-</italic>1, and 1 μM of ang II + over-<italic>TIMP1</italic>. (D,E) WB analysis of the protein expression levels of the TGF-β/Smad3 signaling pathway components in rat cardiac fibroblasts, including TGF-β1, phosphorylated Smad2 (p-Smad2), phosphorylated Smad3 (p-Smad3), Smad2, and Smad3. The experimental groups of rat cardiac fibroblasts were as follows: control, 1 μM of ang II, 1 μM of ang II + NC, 1 μM of ang II + si-<italic>TIMP1-</italic>1, and 1 μM of ang II + over-<italic>TIMP1</italic>. Each experiment was performed with at least three biological replicates. *, P&lt;0.05. <italic>TIMP1</italic>, tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinases-1; ang II, angiotensin II; NC, negative control; qRT-PCR, quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction; WB, Western blotting.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="jtd-17-06-4249-f5.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/29d6/12268815/dde7fb3da9c4/jtd-17-06-4249-f5.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 2048?><?original-width 1688?><?scaled-height 819?><?scaled-width 675?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="jtd-17-06-4249-f5.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/29d6/12268815/3829d29b9407/jtd-17-06-4249-f5.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec></sec><sec id="sec27" disp-level="1"><title>Discussion</title><p>AF is a common arrhythmia characterized by rapid and irregular contractions of the atria, and its mechanisms and treatments have been the subject of extensive research (<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Atrial fibrosis, a change in the organization of the atria, is an important factor in the development and persistence of AF. Cardiac fibrosis provides a structural substrate for the development of AF by altering the atria’s electrophysiological properties (<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Numerous studies have highlighted a close association between alterations in <italic>TIMP</italic> and <italic>MMP</italic> tissue inhibitors and the upregulation of collagen. Yuan<italic> et al. </italic>observed a downregulation of microRNA-1 (miRNA-1) and an upregulation of microRNA-21 (miRNA-21) in older adults with AF that correlated with changes in myocardial fibrosis, cell apoptosis, and key genes associated with atrial remodeling, such as <italic>TIMP1</italic>, <italic>MMP9</italic>, <italic>BCL</italic>-<italic>2</italic>, and <italic>Bax </italic>(<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). A study by Yuan<italic> et al. </italic>showed that Quyu Fange, a Chinese medicine formula, affects rats with hypertensive heart failure caused by diabetes and high blood pressure, which preserves ejection fraction (<xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). This was attributed to the modification of the ang II/TGF-β1/Smad2/3 signaling pathway, attenuation of atrial and ventricular remodeling, circumvention of myocardial fibrosis and hypertrophy, and marked enhancement of cardiac function.</p><p>Based on these findings, we conducted a study in which we thoroughly analyzed the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE115574" ext-link-type="uri">GSE115574</ext-link> dataset and performed DEG screening and enrichment analysis. It was found that DEGs related to AF were primarily involved in collagen fibrils and the organization of the ECM. This connection underscores the significance of structural remodeling in AF, particularly the production and enrichment of microfibrils and ECM receptor interactions, indicating a complex interplay between cell adhesion and signaling. Furthermore, as the pathways are linked to protein digestion and absorption, as well as myocardial contraction, this suggests that metabolic and contractile dysfunction might contribute to the initiation and persistence of AF. These findings indicate the potential of these pathways to serve as biomarkers or therapeutic targets for the heart remodeling associated with AF. Subsequent analysis identified seven key intersection genes (<italic>BGN</italic>, <italic>COL1A1</italic>, <italic>COL1A2</italic>, <italic>COL3A1</italic>, <italic>FMOD</italic>, <italic>THBS2</italic>, and <italic>TIMP1</italic>) that were highly expressed in AF samples. This finding was corroborated by analysis of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE14975" ext-link-type="uri">GSE14975</ext-link> dataset, underscoring the close association between these genes and AF.</p><p>In addition to <italic>TIMP1</italic>, other genes associated with AF have been identified. Among them, <italic>COL1A1</italic>, <italic>COL1A2</italic>, and <italic>COL3A1</italic> are all crucial structural proteins within the ECM (<xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Dysregulation of these collagen genes and the ensuing fibrosis have been shown to cause abnormal atrial structure, potentially inducing or perpetuating AF. Through bioinformatics analysis, Zhou<italic> et al. </italic>identified <italic>FMOD</italic> as being associated with AG comorbidity and significantly associated with ECM and nicotinamide metabolism, among other processes (<xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). In a study of 18 patients, Van den Berg<italic> et al. </italic>observed that the elevated expression of <italic>COL1A1</italic>, <italic>COL3A1</italic>, <italic>THBS2</italic>, and <italic>BGN</italic> may be associated with the sporadic onset of AF (<xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>).</p><p>ang II is a peptide hormone essential to the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (<xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). The transformation of ang I to ang II is carried out by the ang-converting enzyme (<xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). It acts as a potent vasoconstrictor, leading to an increase in blood pressure by a narrowing of the blood vessels. Moreover, ang II has been implicated in cardiovascular remodeling, inflammation, and fibrosis (<xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). <italic>TGF</italic>-β, belonging to the TGF-β superfamily, is a multifunctional cytokine essential for tissue repair, immunological response, and embryonic development (<xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). The TGF-β/Smad signaling pathway is frequently linked to the development of atrial fibrosis in the setting of AF, which contributes to the formation of arrhythmogenic substrate in the atria (<xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Furthermore, Xing<italic> et al. </italic>demonstrated the potent antifibrotic effects of Decoction of White Aconite in an isoproterenol (ISO)-induced cardiac fibrosis rat model, potentially operating through the Gal-3/TGF-β/Smad signaling pathway by reducing metabolic disturbances and preventing collagen formation (<xref rid="r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). The review by Luo<italic> et al. </italic>indicated that TGF-β promotes atrial fibrosis by activating the SMAD and HESMAD signaling pathways, leading to atrial structural remodeling, thereby increasing the risk of AF (<xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). We used ang II to induce rat atrial fibroblasts to simulate the pathological state of AF. <italic>In vitro </italic>experimental results showed that ang II induced upregulation of <italic>TIMP1</italic> expression in rat cardiac fibroblasts in a dose- and time-dependent manner. This may be attributed to the activation of the TGF-β/Smad signaling pathway (a key regulator of cardiac fibrosis) by ang II treatment, thereby positively regulating the expression of <italic>TIMP1</italic>, a downstream effector molecule of the pathway. This time dependence may be related to the accumulation or stabilization of certain components in the signal transduction pathway. In the future, we will continue to explore these potential mechanisms and study the suitability of <italic>TIMP1</italic> as a therapeutic target for AF.</p><p>In the context of cardiac tissue, collagen I and collagen III, as pivotal ECM proteins, perform vital functions in preserving the heart’s normal structure and functionality (<xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). Excessive synthesis of these proteins can lead to fibrosis, impacting cardiac structure and function (<xref rid="r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Myocardial fibrosis, a pathological process of structural remodeling in AF, has been extensively studied. A study by Nenna<italic> et al. </italic>found that collagen I and collagen III were upregulated in patients with postoperative AF, leading to increased myocardial fibrosis, which may be mediated by TGF-β signaling and ultimately increase the risk of postoperative AF (<xref rid="r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Liang<italic> et al. </italic>detected the up-regulation of TGF-β1, α-SMA, collagen I, and collagen III in an AF model, which was accompanied by aggravated atrial fibrosis. Adding glycyrrhetinic acid (GA) could inhibit the expression of these fibrosis markers, thereby alleviating AF (<xref rid="r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). A study by Yao<italic> et al. </italic>revealed that downregulation of <italic>MIAT</italic> reduces the atrial fibrosis induced by AF, which is attributed to decreased levels of collagen I, collagen III, CTGF, and TGF-β1 (<xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). Additionally, Odeh<italic> et al. </italic>reported that a significant increase in collagen remodeling markers was significantly correlated with inflammatory markers, suggesting that inflammation may promote AF by regulating collagen metabolism. In addition, abnormal collagen remodeling may lead to atrial fibrosis and cardiac structural remodeling, thereby increasing the susceptibility to AF (<xref rid="r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). Our experiments assessed the impact of ang II and the effects of both <italic>TIMP1</italic> knockdown and overexpression on collagen I, collagen III, and the proteins associated with the TGF-β/Smad pathway. We found that <italic>TIMP1</italic> modulates the expression of fibrosis-related markers through the TGF-β/Smad3 pathway. These findings support the use of <italic>TIMP1</italic> as a target for AF therapy. By regulating <italic>TIMP1</italic> expression or its function in cardiac fibrosis, it may help to slow or reverse the progression of AF. Our findings help to clarify the intricate network of molecular mechanisms involved in cardiac fibrosis regulation.</p><p>Targeting <italic>TIMP1</italic> in AF treatment faces several challenges. <italic>TIMP1</italic> is involved in multiple physiological processes, so inhibiting it could cause unintended side effects. Additionally, the body might compensate by upregulating other related pathways, potentially negating the therapeutic effects. AF’s heterogeneity means <italic>TIMP1</italic> may affect different patient subgroups variably, making it crucial to identify who would benefit most from such therapies. Finally, developing delivery systems that specifically target the atrial myocardium without systemic side effects is essential for minimizing off-target interactions. Despite these challenges, several strategies could be employed. Small molecule inhibitors could target <italic>TIMP1</italic>’s active site to reduce fibrosis without disrupting other functions. Gene therapy using siRNA or CRISPR/Cas9 could selectively knock down <italic>TIMP1</italic> expression in cardiac fibroblasts. Monoclonal antibodies could neutralize <italic>TIMP1</italic> activity if they are highly specific and effective. Combining <italic>TIMP1</italic> inhibitors with other therapies, such as anti-inflammatory drugs, could enhance efficacy. Identifying biomarkers to predict patient response to <italic>TIMP1</italic>-targeted therapies could also facilitate personalized treatment strategies.</p><p>Our study has several limitations. First, it relied on<italic> in vitro </italic>experiments using rat cardiac fibroblasts, which may not fully reflect the human cardiac environment. Second, proliferation detection was limited to CCK-8 and colony formation assays; direct methods like EdU staining and Ki67 immunofluorescence could provide a more comprehensive assessment. Third, the limited sample size may not represent the broader patient population. Fourth, we focused on short-term effects of ang II on <italic>TIMP1</italic> expression, leaving long-term effects unknown. Fifth, lacking direct evidence from human AF patient samples, such as TIMP1 immunohistochemistry or ELISA data, limits clinical correlation. Finally, other molecules and signaling pathways may also be involved in AF pathogenesis. Future work will include<italic> in vivo </italic>studies, additional proliferation assays, human data collection, and exploring TIMP1’s interactions and regulation.</p></sec><sec id="sec28" disp-level="1"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Our study provides insights into the role of <italic>TIMP1</italic> in AF, particularly highlighting its crucial role in the ang II-induced proliferation and fibrosis of atrial fibroblasts. Through a comprehensive analysis of gene expression profiles and functional experiments within the PPI network, <italic>TIMP1</italic> was identified as a hub gene significantly associated with AF. <italic>In vitro </italic>studies found that the regulation of <italic>TIMP1</italic> expression affected key pathways, specifically the TGF-β1 and Smad2/3 signaling, thereby influencing the response of atrial fibroblasts to ang II. Modulation of <italic>TIMP1</italic> expression significantly affected cell proliferation and the expression of fibrosis markers under ang II stimulation, emphasizing <italic>TIMP1</italic>’s potential as a therapeutic target for alleviating AF fibrosis and its complications. This study provides a theoretical basis for <italic>TIMP1</italic> as a potential biomarker, which may contribute to future improvements in clinical practice and patient management, particularly in assessing treatment efficacy and disease progression. Targeting <italic>TIMP1</italic> may enable the development of new therapies that could slow the progression of atrial fibrosis and provide new options for patients unresponsive to existing treatments. Further studies are needed to elucidate the specific mechanism of action of <italic>TIMP1</italic> in AF and to evaluate the safety and efficacy of<italic> TIMP1</italic>-targeted therapeutic strategies in clinical trials.</p></sec><sec id="sec29" disp-level="1"><title>Supplementary</title><supplementary-material id="supplementary-material1" position="float"><caption><p>The article’s supplementary files as</p></caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="su1" position="anchor"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d67e1043" xlink:href="jtd-17-06-4249-rc.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path 29d6/12268815/20f6c6311a3c/jtd-17-06-4249-rc.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 143895?><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/jtd-2025-1088</object-id></media><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d67e1046" xlink:href="jtd-17-06-4249-coif.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path 29d6/12268815/2e2e6432a9b3/jtd-17-06-4249-coif.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 695504?><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/jtd-2025-1088</object-id></media><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d67e1049" xlink:href="jtd-17-06-4249-supplementary.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path 29d6/12268815/0610ee4c6d5a/jtd-17-06-4249-supplementary.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 119045?><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/jtd-2025-1088</object-id></media></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="ack1" sec-type="ack" disp-level="1"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank Dr. Andrea Colli (University of Pisa, Italy) for the critical comments and valuable advice on this study.</p></sec><sec id="notes1" disp-level="1"><p><italic>Ethical Statement:</italic> The authors are accountable for all aspects of the work in ensuring that questions related to the accuracy or integrity of any part of the work are appropriately investigated and resolved. The study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki and its subsequent amendments.</p></sec><sec id="fn-group1" sec-type="fn-group" disp-level="1"><title>Footnotes</title><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><p><italic>Reporting Checklist:</italic> The authors have completed the MDAR reporting checklist. Available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://jtd.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/jtd-2025-1088/rc" ext-link-type="uri">https://jtd.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/jtd-2025-1088/rc</ext-link></p></fn><fn id="fn4"><p><italic>Funding:</italic> This work was supported by the Shanghai Municipal Health Commission (No. 202340055).</p></fn><fn id="fn5"><p><italic>Conflicts of Interest:</italic> All authors have completed the ICMJE uniform disclosure form (available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://jtd.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/jtd-2025-1088/coif" ext-link-type="uri">https://jtd.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/jtd-2025-1088/coif</ext-link>). The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="sec30" disp-level="1"><title>Data Sharing Statement</title><p>Available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://jtd.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/jtd-2025-1088/dss" ext-link-type="uri">https://jtd.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/jtd-2025-1088/dss</ext-link>
</p><fig id="d67e1088" position="anchor"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jtd-17-06-4249-dss.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path 29d6/12268815/f32a513b1361/jtd-17-06-4249-dss.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 64191?><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/jtd-2025-1088</object-id></media></fig></sec><sec id="ref-list1" sec-type="ref-list" disp-level="1"><title>References</title><sec id="ref-list1_sec2" disp-level="2"><ref-list><ref id="r1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Martin AA, Townsend D. Eating your heart out: endogenous proteases may contribute to atrial stunning following atrial fibrillation treatment.
Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol
2024;327:H504-6. 10.1152/ajpheart.00450.2024
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1152/ajpheart.00450.2024"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38995668"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol&amp;title=Eating your heart out: endogenous proteases may contribute to atrial stunning following atrial fibrillation treatment.&amp;author=AA Martin&amp;author=D Townsend&amp;volume=327&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=H504-6&amp;pmid=38995668&amp;doi=10.1152/ajpheart.00450.2024&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Albertsen IE, Bille J, Piazza G, et al. 
Cardiovascular Risk in Young Patients Diagnosed With Obstructive Sleep Apnea.
J Am Heart Assoc
2024;13:e033506. 10.1161/JAHA.123.033506
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1161/JAHA.123.033506"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11262486"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38563371"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J Am Heart Assoc&amp;title=Cardiovascular Risk in Young Patients Diagnosed With Obstructive Sleep Apnea.&amp;author=IE Albertsen&amp;author=J Bille&amp;author=G Piazza&amp;volume=13&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=e033506&amp;pmid=38563371&amp;doi=10.1161/JAHA.123.033506&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ma Q, Zhu J, Zheng P, et al. 
Global burden of atrial fibrillation/flutter: Trends from 1990 to 2019 and projections until 2044.
Heliyon
2024;10:e24052. 10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e24052
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e24052"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10825430"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38293361"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Heliyon&amp;title=Global burden of atrial fibrillation/flutter: Trends from 1990 to 2019 and projections until 2044.&amp;author=Q Ma&amp;author=J Zhu&amp;author=P Zheng&amp;volume=10&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=e24052&amp;pmid=38293361&amp;doi=10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e24052&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Constante AD, Suarez J, Lourenço G, et al. 
Prevalence, Management, and Outcomes of Atrial Fibrillation in Paediatric Patients: Insights from a Tertiary Cardiology Centre.
Medicina (Kaunas)
2024;60:1505. 10.3390/medicina60091505
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/medicina60091505"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11433662"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39336546"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Medicina (Kaunas)&amp;title=Prevalence, Management, and Outcomes of Atrial Fibrillation in Paediatric Patients: Insights from a Tertiary Cardiology Centre.&amp;author=AD Constante&amp;author=J Suarez&amp;author=G Lourenço&amp;volume=60&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=1505&amp;pmid=39336546&amp;doi=10.3390/medicina60091505&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Mannakkara NN, Khan I, Ghazanfar A, et al. 
Convergent ablation for persistent atrial fibrillation: A UK multicentre perspective.
J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol
2024;35:2039-52. 10.1111/jce.16399
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/jce.16399"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39136365"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol&amp;title=Convergent ablation for persistent atrial fibrillation: A UK multicentre perspective.&amp;author=NN Mannakkara&amp;author=I Khan&amp;author=A Ghazanfar&amp;volume=35&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=2039-52&amp;pmid=39136365&amp;doi=10.1111/jce.16399&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Schotten U, Goette A, Verheule S. Translation of pathophysiological mechanisms of atrial fibrosis into new diagnostic and therapeutic approaches.
Nat Rev Cardiol
2025;22:225-40. 10.1038/s41569-024-01088-w
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41569-024-01088-w"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39443702"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Nat Rev Cardiol&amp;title=Translation of pathophysiological mechanisms of atrial fibrosis into new diagnostic and therapeutic approaches.&amp;author=U Schotten&amp;author=A Goette&amp;author=S Verheule&amp;volume=22&amp;publication_year=2025&amp;pages=225-40&amp;pmid=39443702&amp;doi=10.1038/s41569-024-01088-w&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Hou A, Shi D, Huang H, et al. 
Inflammation pathways as therapeutic targets in angiotensin II induced atrial fibrillation.
Front Pharmacol
2025;16:1515864. 10.3389/fphar.2025.1515864
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3389/fphar.2025.1515864"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11911380"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40098617"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Front Pharmacol&amp;title=Inflammation pathways as therapeutic targets in angiotensin II induced atrial fibrillation.&amp;author=A Hou&amp;author=D Shi&amp;author=H Huang&amp;volume=16&amp;publication_year=2025&amp;pages=1515864&amp;pmid=40098617&amp;doi=10.3389/fphar.2025.1515864&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sygitowicz G, Maciejak-Jastrzębska A, Sitkiewicz D.
A Review of the Molecular Mechanisms Underlying Cardiac Fibrosis and Atrial Fibrillation.
J Clin Med
2021;10:4430. 10.3390/jcm10194430
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/jcm10194430"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8509789"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34640448"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J Clin Med&amp;title=A Review of the Molecular Mechanisms Underlying Cardiac Fibrosis and Atrial Fibrillation.&amp;author=G Sygitowicz&amp;author=A Maciejak-Jastrzębska&amp;author=D. Sitkiewicz&amp;volume=10&amp;publication_year=2021&amp;pages=4430&amp;pmid=34640448&amp;doi=10.3390/jcm10194430&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shi M, Ning Z. In vivo and in vitro investigations of schisandrin B against angiotensin II induced ferroptosis and atrial fibrosis by regulation of the SIRT1 pathway.
Sci Rep
2025;15:6200. 10.1038/s41598-025-89895-0
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41598-025-89895-0"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11842858"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39979353"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Sci Rep&amp;title=In vivo and in vitro investigations of schisandrin B against angiotensin II induced ferroptosis and atrial fibrosis by regulation of the SIRT1 pathway.&amp;author=M Shi&amp;author=Z Ning&amp;volume=15&amp;publication_year=2025&amp;pages=6200&amp;pmid=39979353&amp;doi=10.1038/s41598-025-89895-0&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhang Y, Yuan M, Cai W, et al. 
Prostaglandin I(2) signaling prevents angiotensin II-induced atrial remodeling and vulnerability to atrial fibrillation in mice.
Cell Mol Life Sci
2024;81:264. 10.1007/s00018-024-05259-3
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s00018-024-05259-3"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11335301"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38878214"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Cell Mol Life Sci&amp;title=Prostaglandin I(2) signaling prevents angiotensin II-induced atrial remodeling and vulnerability to atrial fibrillation in mice.&amp;author=Y Zhang&amp;author=M Yuan&amp;author=W Cai&amp;volume=81&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=264&amp;pmid=38878214&amp;doi=10.1007/s00018-024-05259-3&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bode D, Pronto JRD, Schiattarella GG, et al. 
Metabolic remodelling in atrial fibrillation: manifestations, mechanisms and clinical implications.
Nat Rev Cardiol
2024;21:682-700. 10.1038/s41569-024-01038-6
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41569-024-01038-6"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38816507"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Nat Rev Cardiol&amp;title=Metabolic remodelling in atrial fibrillation: manifestations, mechanisms and clinical implications.&amp;author=D Bode&amp;author=JRD Pronto&amp;author=GG Schiattarella&amp;volume=21&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=682-700&amp;pmid=38816507&amp;doi=10.1038/s41569-024-01038-6&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shoari A, Ashja Ardalan A, Dimesa AM, et al. 
Targeting Invasion: The Role of MMP-2 and MMP-9 Inhibition in Colorectal Cancer Therapy.
Biomolecules
2024;15:35. 10.3390/biom15010035
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/biom15010035"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11762759"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39858430"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Biomolecules&amp;title=Targeting Invasion: The Role of MMP-2 and MMP-9 Inhibition in Colorectal Cancer Therapy.&amp;author=A Shoari&amp;author=A Ashja Ardalan&amp;author=AM Dimesa&amp;volume=15&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=35&amp;pmid=39858430&amp;doi=10.3390/biom15010035&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Coates-Park S, Rich JA, Stetler-Stevenson WG, et al. 
The TIMP protein family: diverse roles in pathophysiology.
Am J Physiol Cell Physiol
2024;326:C917-34. 10.1152/ajpcell.00699.2023
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1152/ajpcell.00699.2023"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11193487"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38284123"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Am J Physiol Cell Physiol&amp;title=The TIMP protein family: diverse roles in pathophysiology.&amp;author=S Coates-Park&amp;author=JA Rich&amp;author=WG Stetler-Stevenson&amp;volume=326&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=C917-34&amp;pmid=38284123&amp;doi=10.1152/ajpcell.00699.2023&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Dąbek J, Korzeń D, Sierka O, et al. 
Risk Factors Association with Transcriptional Activity of Metalloproteinase 9 (MMP-9) and Tissue Inhibitor of Metalloproteinases 1 (TIMP-1) Genes in Patients with Heart Failure.
Biomedicines
2024;12:601. 10.3390/biomedicines12030601
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/biomedicines12030601"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10967893"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38540214"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Biomedicines&amp;title=Risk Factors Association with Transcriptional Activity of Metalloproteinase 9 (MMP-9) and Tissue Inhibitor of Metalloproteinases 1 (TIMP-1) Genes in Patients with Heart Failure.&amp;author=J Dąbek&amp;author=D Korzeń&amp;author=O Sierka&amp;volume=12&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=601&amp;pmid=38540214&amp;doi=10.3390/biomedicines12030601&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Li H, Sun W, Wang Z, et al. 
Higher serum tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinase-1 predicts atrial fibrillation recurrence after radiofrequency catheter ablation.
Front Cardiovasc Med
2022;9:961914. 10.3389/fcvm.2022.961914
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3389/fcvm.2022.961914"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9606231"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36312240"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Front Cardiovasc Med&amp;title=Higher serum tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinase-1 predicts atrial fibrillation recurrence after radiofrequency catheter ablation.&amp;author=H Li&amp;author=W Sun&amp;author=Z Wang&amp;volume=9&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;pages=961914&amp;pmid=36312240&amp;doi=10.3389/fcvm.2022.961914&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sun W, Li H, Wang Z, et al. 
Clinical and Laboratory Biomarkers in Paroxysmal Atrial Fibrillation: A Single Center Cross-Sectional Study.
Contrast Media Mol Imaging
2022;2022:7012377. 10.1155/2022/7012377
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1155/2022/7012377"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9259273"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="35845733"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Contrast Media Mol Imaging&amp;title=Clinical and Laboratory Biomarkers in Paroxysmal Atrial Fibrillation: A Single Center Cross-Sectional Study.&amp;author=W Sun&amp;author=H Li&amp;author=Z Wang&amp;volume=2022&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;pages=7012377&amp;pmid=35845733&amp;doi=10.1155/2022/7012377&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Fragão-Marques M, Miranda I, Martins D, et al. 
Atrial matrix remodeling in atrial fibrillation patients with aortic stenosis.
BMC Cardiovasc Disord
2020;20:468. 10.1186/s12872-020-01754-0
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/s12872-020-01754-0"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7603735"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33129260"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=BMC Cardiovasc Disord&amp;title=Atrial matrix remodeling in atrial fibrillation patients with aortic stenosis.&amp;author=M Fragão-Marques&amp;author=I Miranda&amp;author=D Martins&amp;volume=20&amp;publication_year=2020&amp;pages=468&amp;pmid=33129260&amp;doi=10.1186/s12872-020-01754-0&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Martínez-Martínez E, Ibarrola J, Fernández-Celis A, et al. 
Differential Proteomics Identifies Reticulocalbin-3 as a Novel Negative Mediator of Collagen Production in Human Cardiac Fibroblasts.
Sci Rep
2017;7:12192. 10.1038/s41598-017-12305-7
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41598-017-12305-7"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC5610303"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="28939891"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Sci Rep&amp;title=Differential Proteomics Identifies Reticulocalbin-3 as a Novel Negative Mediator of Collagen Production in Human Cardiac Fibroblasts.&amp;author=E Martínez-Martínez&amp;author=J Ibarrola&amp;author=A Fernández-Celis&amp;volume=7&amp;publication_year=2017&amp;pages=12192&amp;pmid=28939891&amp;doi=10.1038/s41598-017-12305-7&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhu X, Zhang X, Gu W, et al. 
ANGPTL4 suppresses the profibrogenic functions of atrial fibroblasts induced by angiotensin II by up-regulating PPARγ.
Iran J Basic Med Sci
2023;26:587-93. 10.22038/IJBMS.2023.69196.15077
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.22038/IJBMS.2023.69196.15077"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10083826"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37051105"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Iran J Basic Med Sci&amp;title=ANGPTL4 suppresses the profibrogenic functions of atrial fibroblasts induced by angiotensin II by up-regulating PPARγ.&amp;author=X Zhu&amp;author=X Zhang&amp;author=W Gu&amp;volume=26&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;pages=587-93&amp;pmid=37051105&amp;doi=10.22038/IJBMS.2023.69196.15077&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Liu Y, Yin Z, Xu X, et al. 
Crosstalk between the activated Slit2-Robo1 pathway and TGF-β1 signalling promotes cardiac fibrosis.
ESC Heart Fail
2021;8:447-60. 10.1002/ehf2.13095
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1002/ehf2.13095"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7835586"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33236535"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=ESC Heart Fail&amp;title=Crosstalk between the activated Slit2-Robo1 pathway and TGF-β1 signalling promotes cardiac fibrosis.&amp;author=Y Liu&amp;author=Z Yin&amp;author=X Xu&amp;volume=8&amp;publication_year=2021&amp;pages=447-60&amp;pmid=33236535&amp;doi=10.1002/ehf2.13095&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shahrajabian MH, Sun W. The Significance and Importance of dPCR, qPCR, and SYBR Green PCR Kit in the Detection of Numerous Diseases.
Curr Pharm Des
2024;30:169-79. 10.2174/0113816128276560231218090436
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.2174/0113816128276560231218090436"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38243947"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Curr Pharm Des&amp;title=The Significance and Importance of dPCR, qPCR, and SYBR Green PCR Kit in the Detection of Numerous Diseases.&amp;author=MH Shahrajabian&amp;author=W Sun&amp;volume=30&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=169-79&amp;pmid=38243947&amp;doi=10.2174/0113816128276560231218090436&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Rafaqat S, Noshair I, Arif M, et al. 
Atrial fibrillation and adipokines: a pathophysiological perspective.
Cardiovascular Innovations and Applications
2024;9:946.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Cardiovascular Innovations and Applications&amp;title=Atrial fibrillation and adipokines: a pathophysiological perspective.&amp;author=S Rafaqat&amp;author=I Noshair&amp;author=M Arif&amp;volume=9&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=946&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Iwamiya S, Ihara K, Nitta G, et al. 
Atrial Fibrillation and Underlying Structural and Electrophysiological Heterogeneity.
Int J Mol Sci
2024;25:10193. 10.3390/ijms251810193
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/ijms251810193"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11432636"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39337682"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Int J Mol Sci&amp;title=Atrial Fibrillation and Underlying Structural and Electrophysiological Heterogeneity.&amp;author=S Iwamiya&amp;author=K Ihara&amp;author=G Nitta&amp;volume=25&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=10193&amp;pmid=39337682&amp;doi=10.3390/ijms251810193&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yuan K, Zhao P, Wang L. Molecular mechanism of atrial remodeling in patients with aging atrial fibrillation under the expression of microRNA-1 and microRNA-21.
Bioengineered
2021;12:12905-16. 10.1080/21655979.2021.2008668
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1080/21655979.2021.2008668"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8810186"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34957910"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Bioengineered&amp;title=Molecular mechanism of atrial remodeling in patients with aging atrial fibrillation under the expression of microRNA-1 and microRNA-21.&amp;author=K Yuan&amp;author=P Zhao&amp;author=L Wang&amp;volume=12&amp;publication_year=2021&amp;pages=12905-16&amp;pmid=34957910&amp;doi=10.1080/21655979.2021.2008668&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yuan P, Liu J, Xiong S, et al. 
Effects and mechanism of Compound Qidan Formula on rats with HFpEF induced by hypertension and diabetes mellitus based on Ang II/TGF-β1/Smads signaling pathway.
J Ethnopharmacol
2023;313:116558. 10.1016/j.jep.2023.116558
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.jep.2023.116558"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37116729"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J Ethnopharmacol&amp;title=Effects and mechanism of Compound Qidan Formula on rats with HFpEF induced by hypertension and diabetes mellitus based on Ang II/TGF-β1/Smads signaling pathway.&amp;author=P Yuan&amp;author=J Liu&amp;author=S Xiong&amp;volume=313&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;pages=116558&amp;pmid=37116729&amp;doi=10.1016/j.jep.2023.116558&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wesp V, Scholz L, Ziermann-Canabarro JM, et al. 
Constructing networks for comparison of collagen types.
J Integr Bioinform
2024;21:20240020. 10.1515/jib-2024-0020
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1515/jib-2024-0020"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11602231"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38997817"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J Integr Bioinform&amp;title=Constructing networks for comparison of collagen types.&amp;author=V Wesp&amp;author=L Scholz&amp;author=JM Ziermann-Canabarro&amp;volume=21&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=20240020&amp;pmid=38997817&amp;doi=10.1515/jib-2024-0020&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhou M, Xu Y, Zhang L, et al. 
Comprehensive bioinformatics analysis of hub genes in ischemic heart failure and atrial fibrillation.
Front Cardiovasc Med
2025;12:1499065. 10.3389/fcvm.2025.1499065
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3389/fcvm.2025.1499065"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11891352"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40066352"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Front Cardiovasc Med&amp;title=Comprehensive bioinformatics analysis of hub genes in ischemic heart failure and atrial fibrillation.&amp;author=M Zhou&amp;author=Y Xu&amp;author=L Zhang&amp;volume=12&amp;publication_year=2025&amp;pages=1499065&amp;pmid=40066352&amp;doi=10.3389/fcvm.2025.1499065&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">van den Berg NWE, Kawasaki M, Fabrizi B, et al. 
Epicardial and endothelial cell activation concurs with extracellular matrix remodeling in atrial fibrillation.
Clin Transl Med
2021;11:e558. 10.1002/ctm2.558
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1002/ctm2.558"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8567047"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34841686"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Clin Transl Med&amp;title=Epicardial and endothelial cell activation concurs with extracellular matrix remodeling in atrial fibrillation.&amp;author=NWE van den Berg&amp;author=M Kawasaki&amp;author=B Fabrizi&amp;volume=11&amp;publication_year=2021&amp;pages=e558&amp;pmid=34841686&amp;doi=10.1002/ctm2.558&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Szczepanska-Sadowska E.
Interplay of Angiotensin Peptides, Vasopressin, and Insulin in the Heart: Experimental and Clinical Evidence of Altered Interactions in Obesity and Diabetes Mellitus.
Int J Mol Sci
2024;25:1310. 10.3390/ijms25021310
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/ijms25021310"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10816525"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38279313"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Int J Mol Sci&amp;title=Interplay of Angiotensin Peptides, Vasopressin, and Insulin in the Heart: Experimental and Clinical Evidence of Altered Interactions in Obesity and Diabetes Mellitus.&amp;author=E. Szczepanska-Sadowska&amp;volume=25&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=1310&amp;pmid=38279313&amp;doi=10.3390/ijms25021310&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Okal EF, Romero PA, Heinzelman P. Droplet microfluidic screening to engineer angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) catalytic activity.
J Biol Eng
2025;19:12. 10.1186/s13036-025-00482-3
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/s13036-025-00482-3"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11792573"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39901286"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J Biol Eng&amp;title=Droplet microfluidic screening to engineer angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) catalytic activity.&amp;author=EF Okal&amp;author=PA Romero&amp;author=P Heinzelman&amp;volume=19&amp;publication_year=2025&amp;pages=12&amp;pmid=39901286&amp;doi=10.1186/s13036-025-00482-3&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Clark CR, Khalil RA. Regulation of vascular angiotensin II type 1 and type 2 receptor and angiotensin-(1-7)/MasR signaling in normal and hypertensive pregnancy.
Biochem Pharmacol
2024;220:115963. 10.1016/j.bcp.2023.115963
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.bcp.2023.115963"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10860599"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38061417"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Biochem Pharmacol&amp;title=Regulation of vascular angiotensin II type 1 and type 2 receptor and angiotensin-(1-7)/MasR signaling in normal and hypertensive pregnancy.&amp;author=CR Clark&amp;author=RA Khalil&amp;volume=220&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=115963&amp;pmid=38061417&amp;doi=10.1016/j.bcp.2023.115963&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Tie Y, Tang F, Peng D, et al. 
TGF-beta signal transduction: biology, function and therapy for diseases.
Mol Biomed
2022;3:45. 10.1186/s43556-022-00109-9
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/s43556-022-00109-9"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9761655"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36534225"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Mol Biomed&amp;title=TGF-beta signal transduction: biology, function and therapy for diseases.&amp;author=Y Tie&amp;author=F Tang&amp;author=D Peng&amp;volume=3&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;pages=45&amp;pmid=36534225&amp;doi=10.1186/s43556-022-00109-9&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lai YJ, Tsai FC, Chang GJ, et al. 
miR-181b targets semaphorin 3A to mediate TGF-β-induced endothelial-mesenchymal transition related to atrial fibrillation.
J Clin Invest
2022;132:e142548. 10.1172/JCI142548
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1172/JCI142548"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9246393"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="35775491"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J Clin Invest&amp;title=miR-181b targets semaphorin 3A to mediate TGF-β-induced endothelial-mesenchymal transition related to atrial fibrillation.&amp;author=YJ Lai&amp;author=FC Tsai&amp;author=GJ Chang&amp;volume=132&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;pages=e142548&amp;pmid=35775491&amp;doi=10.1172/JCI142548&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Xing Z, Yang C, Feng Y, et al. 
Understanding aconite’s anti-fibrotic effects in cardiac fibrosis.
Phytomedicine
2024;122:155112. 10.1016/j.phymed.2023.155112
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.phymed.2023.155112"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37924690"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Phytomedicine&amp;title=Understanding aconite’s anti-fibrotic effects in cardiac fibrosis.&amp;author=Z Xing&amp;author=C Yang&amp;author=Y Feng&amp;volume=122&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=155112&amp;pmid=37924690&amp;doi=10.1016/j.phymed.2023.155112&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Luo B, Zheng R, Shi C, et al. 
DACT2 modulates atrial fibrillation through TGF/β and Wnt signaling pathways.
Heliyon
2024;10:e36050. 10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e36050
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e36050"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11367123"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39224277"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Heliyon&amp;title=DACT2 modulates atrial fibrillation through TGF/β and Wnt signaling pathways.&amp;author=B Luo&amp;author=R Zheng&amp;author=C Shi&amp;volume=10&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=e36050&amp;pmid=39224277&amp;doi=10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e36050&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wang X, Chen X, Wang Y, et al. 
Astragaloside IV alleviates inflammation and improves myocardial metabolism in heart failure mice with preserved ejection fraction.
Front Pharmacol
2024;15:1467132. 10.3389/fphar.2024.1467132
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3389/fphar.2024.1467132"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11618538"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39640484"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Front Pharmacol&amp;title=Astragaloside IV alleviates inflammation and improves myocardial metabolism in heart failure mice with preserved ejection fraction.&amp;author=X Wang&amp;author=X Chen&amp;author=Y Wang&amp;volume=15&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=1467132&amp;pmid=39640484&amp;doi=10.3389/fphar.2024.1467132&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yang W, Wang Y, Li H, et al. 
Enhanced TfR1 Recognition of Myocardial Injury after Acute Myocardial Infarction with Cardiac Fibrosis via Pre-Degrading Excess Fibrotic Collagen.
Biology (Basel)
2024;13:213. 10.3390/biology13040213
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/biology13040213"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11048469"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38666825"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Biology (Basel)&amp;title=Enhanced TfR1 Recognition of Myocardial Injury after Acute Myocardial Infarction with Cardiac Fibrosis via Pre-Degrading Excess Fibrotic Collagen.&amp;author=W Yang&amp;author=Y Wang&amp;author=H Li&amp;volume=13&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=213&amp;pmid=38666825&amp;doi=10.3390/biology13040213&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Nenna A, Laudisio A, Taffon C, et al. 
Intestinal Microbiota and Derived Metabolites in Myocardial Fibrosis and Postoperative Atrial Fibrillation.
Int J Mol Sci
2024;25:6037. 10.3390/ijms25116037
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/ijms25116037"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11173100"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38892223"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Int J Mol Sci&amp;title=Intestinal Microbiota and Derived Metabolites in Myocardial Fibrosis and Postoperative Atrial Fibrillation.&amp;author=A Nenna&amp;author=A Laudisio&amp;author=C Taffon&amp;volume=25&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=6037&amp;pmid=38892223&amp;doi=10.3390/ijms25116037&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Liang H, Zhang N, Zhao L, et al. 
Glycyrrhetinic acid alleviates atrial fibrillation by inhibiting the expression of PIM1.
Chemical Biology &amp; Drug Design
2024;103:e14448.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Chemical Biology &amp; Drug Design&amp;title=Glycyrrhetinic acid alleviates atrial fibrillation by inhibiting the expression of PIM1.&amp;author=H Liang&amp;author=N Zhang&amp;author=L Zhao&amp;volume=103&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=e14448&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yao L, Zhou B, You L, et al. 
LncRNA MIAT/miR-133a-3p axis regulates atrial fibrillation and atrial fibrillation-induced myocardial fibrosis.
Mol Biol Rep
2020;47:2605-17. 10.1007/s11033-020-05347-0
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s11033-020-05347-0"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32130618"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Mol Biol Rep&amp;title=LncRNA MIAT/miR-133a-3p axis regulates atrial fibrillation and atrial fibrillation-induced myocardial fibrosis.&amp;author=L Yao&amp;author=B Zhou&amp;author=L You&amp;volume=47&amp;publication_year=2020&amp;pages=2605-17&amp;pmid=32130618&amp;doi=10.1007/s11033-020-05347-0&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Odeh A, Dungan GD, Hoppensteadt D, et al. 
Interrelationship Between Inflammatory Biomarkers and Collagen Remodeling Proteins in Atrial Fibrillation.
Clin Appl Thromb Hemost
2023;29:10760296231165055. 10.1177/10760296231165055
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1177/10760296231165055"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10034319"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36941787"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Clin Appl Thromb Hemost&amp;title=Interrelationship Between Inflammatory Biomarkers and Collagen Remodeling Proteins in Atrial Fibrillation.&amp;author=A Odeh&amp;author=GD Dungan&amp;author=D Hoppensteadt&amp;volume=29&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;pages=10760296231165055&amp;pmid=36941787&amp;doi=10.1177/10760296231165055&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></sec></sec></body><sub-article article-type="reviewer-report" id="jtd-17-06-4249-prf"><front><journal-meta><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Thoracic Disease</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title>J Thorac Dis</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group></journal-meta><article-meta><title-group><article-title>Peer Review File</article-title></title-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://jtd.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/jtd-2025-1088/prf" ext-link-type="uri">https://jtd.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/jtd-2025-1088/prf</ext-link></p><fig id="d67e2323" position="anchor"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jtd-17-06-4249-prf.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path 29d6/12268815/40cebffdd725/jtd-17-06-4249-prf.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 90426?></media></fig></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="associated-data" id="_ad93_"><front><article-meta><title-group><article-title>Associated Data</article-title></title-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="_adsm93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="supplementary-materials" disp-level="1"><title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material1_reqid_" position="float"><caption><p>The article’s supplementary files as</p></caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material2_reqid_" position="anchor"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jtd-17-06-4249-rc.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path 29d6/12268815/20f6c6311a3c/jtd-17-06-4249-rc.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 143895?><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/jtd-2025-1088</object-id></media><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jtd-17-06-4249-coif.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path 29d6/12268815/2e2e6432a9b3/jtd-17-06-4249-coif.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 695504?><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/jtd-2025-1088</object-id></media><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jtd-17-06-4249-supplementary.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path 29d6/12268815/0610ee4c6d5a/jtd-17-06-4249-supplementary.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 119045?><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/jtd-2025-1088</object-id></media></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="_adda93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="data-availability-statement" disp-level="1"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>Available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://jtd.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/jtd-2025-1088/dss" ext-link-type="uri">https://jtd.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/jtd-2025-1088/dss</ext-link>
</p><fig id="db_da_fig6_reqid_" position="anchor"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jtd-17-06-4249-dss.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path 29d6/12268815/f32a513b1361/jtd-17-06-4249-dss.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 64191?><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/jtd-2025-1088</object-id></media></fig></sec></body></sub-article></article>